<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Certain speeches made upon the day of the yearly election of officers in the city of Gloucester ... by John Dorney, Esq. ...</title>
            <author>Dorney, John, b. 1604 or 5.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 163 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 46 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36363</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12010245</idno>
  <idno type="VID">52385</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240924857</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1932</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16721</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12010245</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36363)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52385)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 64:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Certain speeches made upon the day of the yearly election of officers in the city of Gloucester ... by John Dorney, Esq. ...</title>
                  <author>Dorney, John, b. 1604 or 5.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 83, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A.M. for Tho. Underhill ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First ed. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Yale University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Gloucester (England) --  Officials and employees.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:52385:1"/>
            <head>Insignia Civitatis Gloucestriae.</head>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>city of Gloucester shield</figDesc>
                  <p>FIDES INVICTA TRIVMPHAT</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:52385:1"/>
            <head>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. A Copy of Verses made for, and presented to the City of <hi>Gloucester.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>WHen <hi>Civil broyles</hi> through <hi>Englands</hi> fields spred far;</l>
               <l>And <hi>Regall Power</hi> oppos'd the <hi>Popular;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>This famous <hi>City</hi> then unconquer'd stood:</l>
               <l>And was the <hi>Ramoth-Gilead</hi> of the good.</l>
               <l>It was a <hi>Refuge</hi> for poor <hi>Christians,</hi> when</l>
               <l>This Land was over-runne by bloudy men;</l>
               <l>The <hi>Noahs-Ark</hi> where shelter sweet was found</l>
               <l>For <hi>males</hi> and <hi>females,</hi> when <hi>Mars</hi> ran the round.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Let this fair <hi>City</hi> long and long encrease,</l>
               <l>With <hi>incorrupted</hi> truth, health, wealth and peace;</l>
               <l>Let the <hi>unslumbring God</hi> for ever dwell,</l>
               <l>And here (with waking Eyes) stand <hi>sentinell,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To keep this place: and ever govern here</l>
               <l>Till <hi>Phoebus</hi> quite forsakes this <hi>Hemi-sphaere.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And let our people ever thankfull be,</l>
               <l>To the great God of our felicitie.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>By SAM. KENRICK one of the<lb/> Ministers of the said City.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:52385:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52385:2"/>
            <p>CERTAIN SPEECHES Made upon the day of the Yearly Election of OFFICERS in the City of <hi>Gloucester.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being in the Charter-Language of the said City, <hi>Die Lunae prox' post Festum S. Michaelis Archangeli.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>John Dorney,</hi> Esq; Town-Clerke of the said City.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Ovid. de Ponto.</bibl>
               <l>Turpe referre pedem, nec passu stare tenaci,</l>
               <l>Turpe laborantem deseruisse ratem.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>A. M.</hi> for <hi>Tho. Ʋnderhill</hi> at the Anchor and Bible in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, MDCLIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:52385:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52385:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the Right Worshipfull</hi> William Capell <hi>Esquire, Maior of the City of</hi> Glocester, <hi>the Worshipfull Aldermen his Brethren, and the rest of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Councell of the said City.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome Reasons having been prevalent Motives with me now to expose that to open view, which at several times was by me publiquely delivered in your City; and considering what relations both the matter and my self have to you (the Representative thereof) I held my self obliged to present the same unto you, to whom it doth most properly belong. And I do entreat your favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Acceptance thereof, desiring that
<pb facs="tcp:52385:4"/> it may not only serve you as your Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brancer, but that it may serve me also as a pledge of my gratitude for the many favours which I have received from you, to whom I do professedly acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge my self to remain,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Devoted Servant,<lb/>
                  <hi>JO. DORNEY.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="collection_of_speeches">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:52385:4"/>
            <head>SPEECHES Upon the Daies of Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of Civil Officers in the City of <hi>Gloucester,</hi> during the late Civil War, and since.</head>
            <div type="speech">
               <head>Dionisio Wise Arm' Majore.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath been a Custome (Worthy <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Octob.</hi> 2. <hi>A<seg rend="sup">o</seg>
                     </hi> 1643<seg rend="sup">o</seg>
                  </note> Citizens) upon such <hi>Solemnities</hi> to make some Narration of the <hi>Antiquity</hi> and Honour of your <hi>City;</hi> But leaving that to better <hi>Antiquaries,</hi> I hope it will suffice <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o tell you rather what your <hi>City</hi> is at present, <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hen what it hath been in times past; yea, it might suffice, considering the present state of <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hings abroad, to tell you what your <hi>City</hi> is not <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s well as what it is: for howsoever I speak, it will be, it must be <hi>In honorem Gloucestriae,</hi> to the honour of <hi>Gloucester.</hi> Your <hi>City</hi> is as it was,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:52385:5"/> many others have known sad changes; but as you heard lately in a sacred Assembly, <hi>Gloucester</hi> is <hi>Gloucester;</hi> others the objects of <hi>pitty,</hi> whilest yours of <hi>envy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Your <hi>City</hi> is more then it was, more in <hi>desert</hi> therefore more in <hi>renown.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Your <hi>City</hi> is a free <hi>City,</hi> so free from <hi>Popery,</hi> and so free from <hi>tyranny,</hi> that your consciences are not enforced to be <hi>ensnared</hi> by the one, nor yet your persons to be <hi>enslaved</hi> by the other. There is such a <hi>purity</hi> in your sacred services, that you may say They are gods. There is such a <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty</hi> in your estates, that you may say They are your own.</p>
               <p>Your <hi>City</hi> is a famous <hi>City,</hi> famous for fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and famous for constancy in the cause of God and of the Common-wealth.</p>
               <p>Yea, your <hi>City</hi> is a blessed <hi>City,</hi> a <hi>Domino Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedicta,</hi> the blessed of the Lord. He was in the midst of it, when the enemies besieged it; he fought for you when they fought against you; He in his great mercy preserved you from their great fury, and for it <hi>Benedictus sit Dominus,</hi> Let the Lord be blessed. When your passages were stopt on earth, there remained a way open to heaven, to use the sweet expression of one of your Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines. And though your persons were denied <note place="margin">M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                     <hi>Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford.</hi>
                  </note> earthly visits, yet faithfull praiers made by you and for you, had accesse and audience above, and the most High did visit you in your <hi>low estate:</hi> When you were threatned, he encouraged you; assaulted, he defended you; and though you were straightned he enlarged you. Whilest your ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies were near you, your God was with you, and therefore they prevailed not over you. He brought
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:52385:5"/> you means of deliverance from afar, even from the <hi>Metropolis,</hi> the mother City (he reward her <note place="margin">
                     <hi>The City of</hi> London <hi>sent five Regiments of the Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Bands and Aux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iliaries.</hi>
                  </note> for it) and thereby the Enemies removed that were so near, so near to your gates, so near to the accomplishment of their designs. And thus were you <hi>delivered,</hi> yea, thus were you <hi>honoured,</hi> which being premised each of you may with Saint <hi>Paul</hi> say, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, I am a Citizen of no mean or obscure City. But you shall no longer retain your glory and fame, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 21. 39.</note> then you enjoy your God, nor can you longer enjoy your God then you endeavour to maintain his <hi>glory,</hi> who hath made you so <hi>glorious</hi> in the eyes of all well affected to Religion, and the King and Kingdom. It is reported of the <hi>Tyri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> and <hi>Sidonians</hi> that they fettered and chained their gods, that they might not depart from them; but your Divines will tell you, that the way to keep your God is <hi>to depart from evil and to do good,</hi> then may you expect that he that hath kept you, and delivered you, will continue to be your keeper and deliverer. God kept and deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you, <hi>Et soli Deo Gloria,</hi> Let him alone have the praise, as the efficient cause, and principall authour of your preservation and deliverance, yet let the instruments employed therein be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged in the second place. And as I wish the <hi>Governour</hi> and the <hi>martiall Officers</hi> may have their due honour, and the <hi>Ministers</hi> for their good praiers, and encouragements in hortatory and consolatory speeches their esteem; so let none deny the <hi>Maior</hi> and <hi>City-Officers</hi> their commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation.</p>
               <p>As for M. <hi>Maior</hi> so transcendent hath his care and pains been for the welfare of this City, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:52385:6"/> therein of the Kingdom, that he deserves the <hi>su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perlative degree,</hi> and not only to be called <hi>Major,</hi> but <hi>Maximus.</hi> He was a Captain as well as a Maior, a sword-man as well as a gown-man; and how well he performed both places civill and martiall for the publike good I need not tell you, his <hi>works</hi> will praise him. His couragious reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, unwearied diligence, untired patience, care in providing, prudence and integrity in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naging, piety towards God, and equity towards man, mercy to the poor, and affability to all, are things praise-worthy; especially being crowned with perseverance in a year of temptations. And therefore having done so well and done so <hi>wisely,</hi> if we should imitate the <hi>Graecians,</hi> then he could be honoured with no lesse then a <hi>graud</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, but howsoever let what is wanting in loud ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations be supplied in true <hi>affections;</hi> and as God hath blessed us by him, so blesse God for him.</p>
               <p>As for M. <hi>Coroner</hi> he had little to do with <hi>ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laries,</hi> whilest so many lived without law: and for his inquisition <hi>super visum corporis,</hi> he was carefull to take them where he might, the <hi>mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall Law</hi> claiming jurisdiction in some cases: But (as an <hi>Alderman)</hi> he hath also put his help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hand to the keeping of your City, and his purse hath been <hi>opened</hi> to the maintaining of the Garison.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Sheriffs</hi> have had few Causes to judge, or Writs to execute; they have not had the power of their <hi>County,</hi> nor yet of their <hi>Goal;</hi> such is the condition of these times. But they have shewed their zeal to justice in standing for the <note place="margin">The Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament.</note>
                  <hi>Highest Court</hi> of the Kingdome, in due atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:52385:6"/> upon the <hi>chiefest Magistrate</hi> of your City, <note place="margin">The Maior.</note> and in observance of the rest of the Justices. How entirely they have loved each other, how fairly they have <hi>demeaued</hi> themselves to all, and how really they have <hi>performed</hi> what they readily <hi>protested</hi> in their endeavours to promote the common good of the Kingdom, and the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular welfare of this City, you all well know.</p>
               <p>As for the <hi>Stewards,</hi> these will tell you of many <hi>arrerages</hi> of Rents; and that their layings out were more then their comings in: yet I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve you will say that they are good <hi>husbands,</hi> and I hope you shall finde them <hi>just Stewards;</hi> and that they also can give account of some good service, not only for the <hi>Chamber,</hi> but the <hi>City;</hi> not only for the <hi>City</hi> but the <hi>Kingdom,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now these <hi>Gentlemen</hi> having thus acted their parts amongst you, are to leave their Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to others who are thought by the Electors worthy to succeed them; and I beleeve when you have heard their names, you will think so to. Their Names are these, <hi>&amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>These I hope will endeavour to preserve and maintain the <hi>honour</hi> of this City, and gain <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> to themselves by the well managing of the publike affairs, which that they may the better do, I wish that as they have the <hi>examples</hi> of their predecessors, so they may have some of their assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance by <hi>councell;</hi> and of you all by <hi>praiers.</hi> And I commend unto them the singular exhortations of the Minister to be repeated by them in their practice.</p>
               <p>These are not to be admitted to their Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as Judges amongst the Jews, by imposition of <note place="margin">See the <hi>Heb. Anti.</hi>
                  </note> hands upon their heads, but by imposition of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:52385:7"/> their hands upon the Book: Whereby they will not only manifest themselves good Protestants, but also good Subjects to their Soveraign, whom the Almighty guide and guard: And to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude let us all say, <hi>Vivat Rex &amp; vigeat Lex,</hi> Let the King live, and the Law bear sway.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="speech">
               <head>II. <hi>Nicolao Webb Arm' Majore.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Am to declare unto you <hi>(Honoured Citizens)</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>A<seg rend="sup">o</seg>
                     </hi> 1644.</note> the names of your new elected Officers: But before I so do, I desire with your leave to speak something concerning <hi>Government,</hi> with a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular reflexion upon this place, something also concerning the <hi>Offices</hi> they are to bear, and the <hi>service</hi> the old Officers have done; lastly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this <hi>change</hi> of Officers, and the grounds thereof; All which I intend to dispatch so brie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fly and truly, that I hope I shall neither offend your <hi>patience,</hi> nor mine own <hi>conscience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Government</hi> doubtlesse is of God, who is the God of order; and <hi>obedience</hi> to the lawfull com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of lawfull Governours (who are called gods) is due by divine right. But the kindes and forms of government, as <hi>Monarchy, Aristo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cracy, Democracy,</hi> the power to be in the Prince, Peers or people, are in Saint <hi>Peters</hi> language (as I take it) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> an humane Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 13.</note> which if it may be affirmed of the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall government of a state, then <hi>a fortiori</hi> of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular corporations. <hi>Government</hi> as it is in it self good, so (being lawfully used) is for good;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:52385:7"/> yea, so necessary to humane society, that without it there would be <hi>disorder,</hi> and thereupon <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion;</hi> for although the Philosopher calls man <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a creature fit for society, yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out government what is a society of men but <hi>Bellua multorum Capitum,</hi> a rude multitude? When did <hi>Israel</hi> come nearer to a <hi>Babel,</hi> then when it was said of that state that they had no King, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> their Law was <hi>Quicquid libet licet,</hi> every one did what pleased himself; and our eyes and ears can witnesse how many and great <hi>disorders</hi> have been in these dissolute times, wherein the <hi>reins</hi> of government are some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what slackned. Far be it therefore for any of us to be in opinion or practice against <hi>Magistracy</hi> as inconsistent with <hi>Christian liberty,</hi> and so become <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> despisers of govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but considering that government is a <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litique</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 10.</note>
                  <hi>predicament</hi> consisting of superiority and inferiority, the parts affording (as in the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall body) mutuall support each to other, for the good of the whole, let us account it an hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinesse to live under <hi>government,</hi> but more espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to be under <hi>good governours.</hi> And having a particular relation to this City and Garrison, let us blesse him that hath blest us this year last past with such Governours in <hi>Civill</hi> and <hi>Martiall</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, as have in some good measure taken care for our souls comfort, and our outward safety, and support.</p>
               <p>If we of this City and Countrey with a seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous consideration look back upon the singular passages and occurrences during their govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, we shall finde many arguments of praise, and engagements of obedience to the most high
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:52385:8"/> God, the Lord of Hosts; who hath made us the <hi>sons of providence</hi> above desert and beyond expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation. For what <hi>provisions</hi> have been made for us? what <hi>protections</hi> have been afforded to us? and what <hi>victories</hi> have been obtained by us? All of them for matter and manner notable, yea ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable; so much of God hath appeared in all, and so little of man, That God in the first place might have all the glory of wise <hi>contrivance,</hi> and effectuall <hi>performance:</hi> yet by his allowance, yea command there is an honour to be given in the second place, to the instruments that he hath ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured in serving his providence, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, honour to whom honour belongs. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for their further encouragement, others imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and your gratefull commemoration, give me leave to be your <hi>remembrancer</hi> of the vigilan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, valour, and fidelity of your noble Governour and the souldiery; and of the praise-worthy en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours and demeanure of M. <hi>Maior</hi> and the City-Officers: Concerning the latter, being most proper for this time and place, I desire to present you with a brief Index of their Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and actions. The <hi>government</hi> of Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths and Cities hath often had mutations, <hi>pro re nata</hi> upon urgent occasions. Among the Jews we reade of the <hi>Patriarchall, judiciary, regall,</hi> and <hi>sacerdotall</hi> powers; and the <hi>Romans</hi> had ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold kindes of Government, as <hi>Kings, Cousuls, Dictators,</hi> &amp;c. There were sometime in <hi>England</hi> seven severall crowned Kings, of seven severall and distinct Kingdoms, and in the end the <hi>West Saxons</hi> got the <hi>Monarchy,</hi> and had the imperiall Diadem; and sithence the <hi>Heptarchy,</hi> many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of years the English Government hath
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:52385:8"/> continued Monarchicall. During which time as many Corporations have been made, so they have had many changes; This among the rest; But they have been still <hi>mutationes in melius,</hi> by royall munificence, in the augmentation of <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges.</hi> In the time of King <hi>John</hi> this was a <hi>Burrough-Town,</hi> and had two <hi>Bailiffs,</hi> and four <hi>chief Burgesses,</hi> the <hi>Bailiffs</hi> in the time of King <hi>Richard the second</hi> were made <hi>Justices</hi> of the <hi>Peace,</hi> King <hi>Richard the third</hi> made it a <hi>Maior-Town,</hi> and a <hi>County,</hi> with two <hi>Hundreds,</hi> subject to 12. <hi>Aldermen</hi> Justices of the Peace; And the <hi>Bai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liffs</hi> of the Town to be <hi>Sheriffs</hi> of the County. King <hi>Henry the eighth</hi> made it a City.</p>
               <p>Now the Government of this City being esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished by <hi>Charter,</hi> the authority of our Justices is more permanent then if it were by <hi>Commission,</hi> which is determinable by the will and death of the King. The Officers do much resemble those of the ancient <hi>Roman State,</hi> first in generall, The <hi>Government</hi> being by a Maior, Aldermen, and Common Councell; It may be termed a Senate, and the Maior <hi>Princeps Senatus,</hi> having alone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst our <hi>Duodecemviri</hi> Ensigns of honour car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried before him, and power alone to convocate the Senate.</p>
               <p>But more particularly, The <hi>Maior</hi> as he is the Kings Lieutenant, so he may be termed <hi>urbis prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectus</hi> one set over the City: in respect of his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amining and judging of matters within the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>Praetor Ʋrbanus,</hi> a City Praetor; as Clark of the Market, <hi>Aedilis Cerealis.</hi> As for the good service M. <hi>Maior</hi> did this last year, though by reason of his personall presence I should give the more sparing <hi>evidence,</hi> yet without any opinion
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:52385:9"/> of flattery, I hope I may say thus much, That I presume you will acknowledge that he was <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the Minister of God for <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 4</note> good; for the good of your persons and estates. His actions will tell you his affection to religion and justice, and his opinion of the justnesse of our cause; It is so well known, that I need not tell you what countenance he gave to Ministers, and their Ministry; what favour he shewed to good men and furtherance of good proceedings; what care he took to keep the Courts and to preserve the City: passing by the watches, which he duly provided, let me bring you to the <note n="*" place="margin">This Mot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to is upon it, A City assaulted by man and saved by God.</note> South gate, which being fallen by the batteries of the late siege, by his care was seasonably rebuilt for strength and ornament.</p>
               <p>And let me put you in minde of his religious desire to perpetuate the memoriall of that won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull <note place="margin">
                     <hi>By Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of May</hi> 10. 1644. <hi>The Maior for the time being.</hi> M. <hi>Hart.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 6.</note> deliverance, not only by Inscriptions but also by annuall Solemnity; yea, further being in the midst of his year and cares made one of the Committee of Parliament for these parts, I beleeve it is well known to most of you, that he had a speciall hand in providing some mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for him whom you heard this day, and have heard so often, who is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> an able Minister of the New Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And also in setting up of lights in divers places abroad, that were in the darknesse of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance. And in particular (to the end also the poor might receive the Gospel) in setling a godly and faithfull Minister at S. <hi>Maries.</hi> Let <note place="margin">M. <hi>Tirer.</hi>
                  </note> me adde that conceiving his place (as things stood) to engage him to have above others <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram animarum</hi> (without institution) he did by
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:52385:9"/> his providence and at his charge take such course that the <hi>City-Lectures</hi> were supplied. For all which and whatsoever else he hath done for Gods honour and the credit and profit of this City, I desire you may not be ungratefull to God, nor unmindefull of him. As for M. <hi>Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> if you enquire what he hath done; I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve he hath <hi>Sans fee</hi> taken many Inquisitions; I wish his successor may not be occasioned to take so many. He had no occasion to give judgement upon Writs of <hi>exigent.</hi> But the sad spectacles he had, especially in the latter part of his year do manifest, that many live without the fear of law though they are not out-lawed. His dilgence as <hi>Coroner</hi> in his enquiries <hi>super visum corporis</hi> hath been great; but his trouble and pains as a Captain of the Trained Band, and as <hi>Surveyor</hi> of the City works were greater. And although he is now to leave the Office of a <hi>Coronor,</hi> yet I <note place="margin">Fortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</note> hope the common good will perswade him to continue the other places; albeit the encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be so small in respect of private advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.</p>
               <p>As for the <hi>Sheriffs</hi> whom some call <hi>Vice-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sules,</hi> I may properly term them <hi>Duumviri Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tales,</hi> in regard of the charge of their prison, and to see Malefactors punished. And albeit there is now a Governour who (being <hi>praetor Marti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alis)</hi> hath made a <hi>Marshalsey</hi> of their prison, yet such care have they taken thereof, as the consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the time would permit. And if you consider how they frequented the Church and the Tolsey; how they were brethren as well in affection as office; how observant they were to superiours, and how courteous to others, you
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:52385:10"/> may all have matter wherefore to commend them, and their Successours wherein to imitate them. As for the Stewards (who are <hi>Quastores Ʋrba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni</hi> or <hi>Aerarij,</hi> because they receive the City moneys, to disburse them upon all occasions of publike expence.) I beleeve they have not laid aside <hi>Aurum vicessimarium</hi> the twentieth part of their receits (as they did in their treasury) for these are not times of laying up, but of laying on, and of laying out. Yet I doubt not but their account will render them both frugall and faithfull, perhaps it will speak of arrears more then former accounts, but you need not marvell at it, for it is the language of the time. And to speak of them all <hi>conjunctim,</hi> why may not I call them all <hi>Tribuni Plebis,</hi> Protectors of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons? Now there is a change of Officers, as there is a vicissitude of things by the revolution of time. I would not have you think that there is here the same reasen as in naturall Philosophy, <hi>Corruptio unius est generatio alterius,</hi> their integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty speaks better for them then so: But as by Charter their authority is granted, so their time is limited. And it is probable that as for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and common good of the City, and to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void papular tumult (as is in the Charter ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed) this annuall election was appointed: for there was a point of policy therein, lest Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers by long continuance might gain an art to deceive or to oppresse.</p>
               <p>Yet the Rules of Administration of the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces remain the same, though the Offices are changed, and are not like the <hi>Praetors</hi> Edicts in <hi>Rome,</hi> which are termed by <hi>Tully, Lex annua,</hi> a Law for a year.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:52385:10"/>
               <p> The Persons that are newly chosen are such, whose deportment I hope will commend their choice, so that to the act of Election, there may be prefaced <hi>bonum factum,</hi> a good deed, as it was wont to the Decrees of the <hi>Roman Senate</hi> in two Capitall letters.</p>
               <p>The Names of the Gentlemen that are cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen are as followeth,—</p>
               <p>There need not to be an interim betwixt their designation to their severall Offices, and their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into them, to enquire <hi>De ambitu;</hi> for they were chosen without suit and competition. Yet first let me say to them, that as they are to go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore others in place, so they are also in good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample; and as they are greater <hi>by Office,</hi> so they ought to be greater <hi>in care,</hi> as well of their own walking, as of their Cities welfare. And as for M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Maior elect, I cannot commend a better rule unto him, then what I have often heard from him, which is, <hi>to execute Justice, and to maintain Truth;</hi> for which purpose, he is to fortifie himself against temptations, because as Magistrates are <hi>Scuta terrae,</hi> so, they are <hi>scuta terrea.</hi> And to you all let me say, that as obedience is due to the Kings lawfull Commands <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as supream; <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 13, 14.</note> so observance is due to these also in their places, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, having a derivative power by Charter from the Ging; to whom they are ready to testifie their <hi>allegiance,</hi> as they have to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament their <hi>fidelity;</hi> and therewithall to perform their respective duties in the government and ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of this City: And if you will not take my word for it, you may see them take their oathes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="speech">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:52385:11"/>
               <head>III. <hi>Lucâ Nourse Armig' Majore.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>GEntlemen,</hi> By the revolution of time, the year <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Octob.</hi> 6. 1645.</note> according to our City computation is at an end, although according to other computations it doth continue for divers moneths. For as the Roman <hi>Annals,</hi> were described and distinguish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Consulships,</hi> so are ours by the Maioralties and Shreivalties of such and such; so that our years do expire with our Officers authority. As they have their <hi>Commencements,</hi> so they have their <hi>periods</hi> together. Looking back upon the year past, I see it <hi>chequered</hi> with various passages of providence, the particulars thereof being so ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious, I passe over with a silent admiration; and at present rather chuse to acquaint you, that our City Officers are wearied with their long atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance upon their severall imployments, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now expect to be <hi>relieved:</hi> they have long born the burthens of publike services, and now are desirous to take their ease, and lay them upon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>shoulders,</hi> such <hi>shoulders</hi> as are deemed well able to bear them, and therefore it is hoped the persons will readily and cheerfully undertake them. To facilitate the work, I shall with your leave, and I hope good liking, prescribe some rules and directions for their carriage: to which you will finde the actions of the present Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers in many things to correspond and agree, and therein I shall propose them for examples to their successors: In some things perhaps you may finde them, or some of them, somewhat deficient, but therein I hope your pardon will be <hi>easie,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:52385:11"/> their services have been <hi>difficult;</hi> where the businesse is great you know <hi>endeavours</hi> are acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted. There is a <hi>dignity</hi> I must acknowledge in bearing publike Offices, yet there is a <hi>difficulty</hi> also in the right performance of duties, especially concerning <hi>government;</hi> which is called an art of arts, as hard as excellent.</p>
               <p>The duties of our Officers are comprised in their oaths they are to take, which do all spring from the same fountain, which is the Kings Charter, where I finde them expressed in the same termes: <hi>i. e.</hi> To execute the Office in all things touching the Office rightly, well and faithfully, and though they are to run in severall <hi>channels,</hi> yet they are to be guided by the streight line of <hi>integrity,</hi> into the ocean of one common end, which is the <hi>publike weale</hi> of this <hi>City</hi> and <hi>County:</hi> which end I hope the severall Officers elected will aym at, and therein I wish they may all meet together in the execution of their Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. The ayde that I shall at present contribute thereunto, is by glossing upon the severall oaths, to give some brief character of the severall Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, which each of the Gentlemen elect may be pleased to accept as their respective <hi>directory,</hi> by way of an additionall, or appendix to that sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable, wholsom and grave covncell given this morning, by him whose person and pains do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve <note place="margin">M. <hi>Nelme.</hi>
                  </note> estimation. I wish more had heard his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, such of us as did I wish may maka a good use of it. I shall take them according to their ranks, and begin first with the <hi>Maior.</hi> The <hi>Maior</hi> is the Kings Lieutenant, and therefore to serve his <hi>lawfull power;</hi> I do not, I may not say his <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>just will.</hi> He is to keep the City to the behoof of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:52385:12"/> the King, alwaies remembring that he is also entrusted with the keeping of the gates by the <hi>Parliament,</hi> where his <hi>power</hi> refides, though his <hi>person</hi> is absent; he is to keep the right of the King, and do the profit of the King; whose Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice is also to protect his people, and maintain their just Rights and Liberties. He is in his place to administer Justice; the <hi>rule</hi> thereof is the <hi>Laws,</hi> the <hi>life</hi> of the Laws is <hi>execution</hi> of them, Justice is by him to be administred to all indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently and seasonably, with wisdom, courage and sincerity. He is the <hi>Head</hi> of the Corporation, set above others, not to insult over them, as if he were above the Laws, but to take care of them by watching for their good, to discover <hi>dangers,</hi> and prevent them; <hi>abuses,</hi> and reform them; <hi>advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages,</hi> and procure them. He is the City <hi>Praetor,</hi> and therefore to go before others, and to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary unto others in all Offices of Piety, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice and humanity. He is <hi>Escheator</hi> of this <hi>City</hi> and <hi>County,</hi> and therein to be subservient to the Court of Wards in the true finding of Offices; the grievances of which Court do much impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune the <hi>Parliament</hi> to finde out a true remedy for their redresse. He is <hi>Steward</hi> and <hi>Marshall</hi> of the Kings houshold within this City and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; but (as things now stand) what he is to do in that respect more then bearing of the title, I know not. He is <hi>Clerk of the Market,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to look that the <hi>weights</hi> and <hi>measures</hi> be just, the <hi>assises of bread and beer</hi> moderate; the <hi>flesh</hi> and <hi>fish</hi> wholsome. To conclude, He is (in an emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent respect) to indeavour to preserve and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the true Religion, together with the peace, the profit, the honour, and health of this <hi>City.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:52385:12"/>
               <p> The next Officer is the <hi>Coroner.</hi> He is also an Officer of trust and authority, of whom the Law takes much notice, as being a very usefull instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Commonwealth in divers respects: chiefly in recording Pleas of the Crown, upon the view of the bodies of such as die unnaturall deaths. Life is one of the greatest favourites of the Law; and therefore upon suspition of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely deaths, this Officer is to make a timely enquiry, using diligence in embracing the oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity for his enquiry, and prudence in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of the fact and circumstances. But I must tell you he is an Officer of Peace, and a principall conservator thereof, not an Officer of warre. The bodies of those that lose their lives in this civill, (I may say unnaturall) warre, are not to be viewed by him, he is to take no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest thereupon; but the supream Judge, the God of vengeance, who rides his circuit thorow the world observeth them, and will make inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition for their blood; which cries aloud against the <hi>authors</hi> and <hi>fomentors</hi> of this destructive war.</p>
               <p>The Sheriffs are Officers appointed for the conservation of the peace of the County, and the supportation of the state of the City; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the said Charter are termed <hi>Bayliffs</hi> of the City and Sheriffs of the County. They are to be employed in Acts judiciall and ministeriall; in the one they are to look to the <hi>cause</hi> more then the <hi>person,</hi> to avoid <hi>partiality;</hi> and in the other, to the <hi>command</hi> more then the <hi>reason,</hi> to avoid <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layes:</hi> In both, wisedom is requisite to <hi>direct,</hi> and resolution to <hi>act.</hi> They are to stand for the fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chises, and to uphold the good customs of the <hi>City</hi> to their power; and therefore to have pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:52385:13"/> spirits in their publike places, making their own private estates, in a more then ordinary manner tributary to the publike state of the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration.</p>
               <p>As for the Stewards and Chamberlaines of this City, they are the City-Receivers, but such as usually pay away more then they receive: They are the <hi>City-Pursbearers,</hi> whose burthens are most heavy when the common purse is most light. As therefore they are to be diligent in collecting, so they are to be provident in dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bursing the publike monies. They are the <hi>City-Treasurers,</hi> intrusted with the Corporation-Seal, Charters and Evidences, together with many utensils belonging to the Corporation; and therefore to take care that they may be rightly used and safely kept. They are the <hi>City Survey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors,</hi> who by their observation and care are to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent ruines, and to repair decayes. And at last, of all their service they are to give a fair accompt, whlch may endure a just survey.</p>
               <p>There is to be in all these Officers, as well as the <hi>Maior,</hi> loyalty to their Soveraign, and fidelity to the City, with respect to the Acts of Common councell; they are all to be <hi>Auxiliaries</hi> in the Government, for the common benefit and credit of the <hi>Corporation:</hi> for which purpose the <hi>Sheriffs</hi> and <hi>Stewards</hi> are specially obliged, to afford the <hi>Maior</hi> their due observance and attendance.</p>
               <p>The representation of these Characters of our City Officers, I hope will have such impression upon the Gentlemen elect, that their practises will be somewhat suitable, and the rather, seeing they are to be fastened upon them with the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred tye of an oath. And I wish such good service
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:52385:13"/> as M. <hi>Maior</hi> and the rest of the old Officers have done in their severall places, by their conformity thereunto, may be so imprinted in your memories, that your due respects may be afforded them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their merits. Particulars I need not expresse, being so well known, otherwise I might begin at M. <hi>Maiors</hi> house, and tell you of his hos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitality; and thence go to the Churches and tell you of his devotion, and how he had a chief hand in the inviting and calling to us of a worthy Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister, <note place="margin">M. <hi>Jack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son.</hi>
                  </note> to supply the room of the Bishop, Dean and Chapter in the Colledge; thence I might lead you to the <hi>Tolsey</hi> and <hi>Bothall,</hi> and tell you of his watchings, justice and equity: thence I might walk to the <hi>key</hi> and <hi>Overs bridge,</hi> and tell you of his extraordinary care and industry. And of the rest I might tell you many things praise worthy, but I forbear. And for them all in generall, I present much thanks unto them all, in the name of the <hi>Corporation.</hi> And now that I may no longer exercise your patience, I come to publish the Names of the new elected Officers, which are as followeth—</p>
               <p>These are the Gentlemen that are chosen to bear the publike Offices of the <hi>Corporation</hi> for the year next following, let them have your helping hands, that their burthens may be the easier born. And before the Gentlemen are sworn, I shall make bold to present my information unto them against two dangerous malignants, that are not to be tolerated in any Parliament Garrison; These are <hi>Impiety</hi> and <hi>iniquity;</hi> with my hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble suit unto them, that for the honour of God, their own honour, and the safety of this City, they will according to their Covenant, (as
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:52385:14"/> much as in them lies) discountenance them, and endeavour their removall from amongst us, by a reall Reformation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="speech">
               <head>IV. <hi>Laurentio Singleton Arm' Majore.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>GEntlemen,</hi> The change of Officers is the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Octob.</hi> 5<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. 1646<seg rend="sup">o</seg>.</note> of this solemn meeting: And it is no marvell that I tell you of a <hi>change;</hi> for experience doth not only teach that men are mortal, but also that their conditions (whil'st they live) are mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, and so are all <hi>sublunary</hi> things wherewithall men have to do: If proof hereof were requisite, I need not go further then <hi>Gloucester</hi> for an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of particulars, for this place hath been the subject of many <hi>changes;</hi> and that in severall respects, both in the times of our forefathers, and in this present <hi>age.</hi> There hath been a <hi>change</hi> in the name of this place; by the <hi>Britains</hi> it was called <hi>Cacr Glowe,</hi> the fair Town; by the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> it was called <hi>Clevum,</hi> and here <hi>Antonine</hi> pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced his Colonie, which was called <hi>Colonia Clevum,</hi> to be as a <hi>yoke</hi> upon the necks of the <hi>Silurcs,</hi> who inhabited betwixt <hi>Severne</hi> and <hi>Wye.</hi> The <hi>Saxons</hi> called it <hi>Gleaucester,</hi> and we <hi>Glocester</hi> or <hi>Glouce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster.</hi> And as it hath been <hi>multinominis,</hi> having had such <hi>changes</hi> in the Appellation; so it hath been <hi>multiformis.</hi> It hath had many changes in build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; for <hi>Cambden</hi> saith, that it was <hi>Fortuito igne</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbs were destroyed to preserve the City.</note>
                  <hi>quater pene absumpta;</hi> and some change hath been since these troubles, by the burning of the <hi>suburbs,</hi> so that it is as a <hi>garment</hi> without <hi>skirts,</hi> which we were willing to part withall, least our enemies
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:52385:14"/> should <hi>sit</hi> upon them. And now in stead of the old suburbs without this City (where there are <hi>ruinarum vestigia)</hi> there is a new street building within the <hi>City.</hi> But my principall meaning is, in respect of the several forms of Government; for this hath been a very ancient Borough: For in the <hi>Charter</hi> of King <hi>John,</hi> it is said, <hi>Secundum</hi>
                  <note place="margin">King John.</note>
                  <hi>Antiquam legem Burgi, quam habuerunt tempore Antecessorum nostrorum.</hi> In which Charter it is appointed that the Common-Councel of the <hi>Burrongh</hi> should choose two <hi>Burgesses,</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent them to the chief-Justice at <hi>Westminster,</hi> for the <hi>prepositure</hi> and government of the Town; and four <hi>Burgesses</hi> to keep the pleas of the Crown; and to see that the other two <hi>justè &amp; legitimè tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctent, tàm pauperes quàm divites.</hi> From a <hi>Bailiff</hi> Town it was <hi>changed</hi> to a <hi>Maior Town</hi> by <hi>R.</hi> 3. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>R.</hi> 3.</note> who to the hundred of <hi>Gloucester</hi> made an addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the two hundreds adjacent, which are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the In-shire, <hi>viz.</hi> the hundreds of <hi>Dudston,</hi> and <hi>Kings Barton.</hi> Afterwards it was made a <hi>City</hi> by <hi>H.</hi> 8. And now it is governed by a <hi>Maior</hi> and <note place="margin">
                     <hi>H.</hi> 8.</note>
                  <hi>eleven Aldermen</hi> Justices of the peace.</p>
               <p>To omit the <hi>changes</hi> in respect of priviledges and <hi>Ensigns of Honour,</hi> there have been divers <hi>changes</hi> in the habits and manners of men inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting within this place; for <hi>tempora mutantur, &amp; nos mutamur.</hi> There have been also divers chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in respect of Trade; for heretofore there was a <hi>Guild Merchant</hi> and a <hi>Mint;</hi> and K. <hi>John</hi> gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto them to be free from <hi>Toll,</hi> and other im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munities; which Trade afterwards decayed. But of late it hath been somewhat revived by some <hi>Gont'</hi> who deserve commendation; and I wish some others would joyn with them in promoting
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:52385:15"/> of the <hi>Merchandizing Trade;</hi> which is the most likely means to make this a flourishing <hi>City.</hi> The trade of <hi>Clothing</hi> is also at a low Ebbe; I wish that that might be set forward, or some other manufacture for keeping of the poor at work. And as there have been <hi>changes</hi> in matters Civil, so there have been also in matters Ecclesiasticall. Here was an Abbey; but <hi>H.</hi> 8. (that <hi>malleus mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nasteriorum)</hi> dissolved the same; and made this a Bishops See, with a Dean and Chapter, of six Prebendaries, and indowed them with revenues, formerly belonging to the said Monastery. Since which time there have been eleven Bishops; yet it is said that there were Bishops here in ancient time, and that the Bishop of this place was called <hi>Episcopus Cluvicusis;</hi> but after the <hi>Saxons</hi> prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, it was under the Bishoprick of <hi>Litchfield,</hi> and after that of <hi>Warwick.</hi> And now instead of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piscopacy (which seems to lye in the dust) a Presbytery is expected; and <hi>Preachers</hi> in stead of <hi>Readers,</hi> and a <hi>spiritual</hi> in stead of a <hi>sormal</hi> and pompous service. And therefore (as I said be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) it is no marvell that I tell you of <hi>changes.</hi> Notwithstanding these changes, this City hath not had such <hi>changes</hi> as some other places have had, which have been forced by <hi>hostile power;</hi> whereas this remains a <hi>Maiden City.</hi> And that it had not such a change, this place hath been the occasion of a great change in the affairs of this Kingdom. And as in the battell fought near <hi>Tewxbury,</hi> there was as it were a period put to the disputes of the Houses of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Lancaster,</hi> for in that battell many of the Lancastrians were cut off; and there amongst others Prince <hi>Edward</hi> the sonne of <hi>Henry</hi> the sixth being apprehended
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:52385:15"/> was slain, so that that side was not able to stand up against <hi>E.</hi> 4. as the Chronicles declare: so the standing out of this place in the late siege, made it the <hi>verticall point</hi> in this civill warre, for from that time the enemies more and more declined; insomuch, as it pleased that reverend Judge Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant <hi>Wilde,</hi> in his late Charge, sitting upon the Commission of <hi>Oyer</hi> and <hi>Terminer</hi> here, to stile <hi>Us</hi> of this place, <hi>The conservators of the Parliament of England,</hi> which was an higher expression then our modesty would have suffered us to have used of our selves. And we account that a part of our happinesse, that as no hurt was intended to our King, so no hurt came to him. And now consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering all these things, we should endeavour that there may be a <hi>change</hi> in our lives; and the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, sithence there is so great a <hi>change</hi> in this place by reason of <hi>sicknesses,</hi> which are as Gods physick for the soul; and if we do not amend thereby I fear our case is desperate. Let us then shew our respect to the <hi>Magistrates,</hi> who are Gods Vicegerents in matters temporall, and to the <hi>Ministers</hi> who are Christs Embassadours in things spirituall; and to carry our selves in such manner of conversation, enjoying the Sunshine of the Gospel, that we may deserve to be called <hi>Probi homines de Glouc.</hi> which was a Title given to the Burgesses of this place in the dark times of <hi>Popery,</hi> as appears by divers Charters.</p>
               <p>And now give me leave to change my Speech, and by an <hi>Apostrophe</hi> to addresse my self to the Officers of the year past; and I shall crave of them leave to change my former course of parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular and personal commendations; for although I might speak of many <hi>prudentiall</hi> Acts and Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:52385:16"/> for the honour and profit of this City, yet I had rather their own actions might be the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of their praises; for by speaking somewhat perhaps I might add to their <hi>applause,</hi> but nothing to their <hi>worth:</hi> for many things I might speak well of them, and yet perhaps I might <hi>malè audire</hi> for so speaking; for when I have heretofore thought I had kept within the bounds of <hi>modesty,</hi> I have scarce escaped the censure of <hi>flattery.</hi> And therefore in these times of Reformation I desire to reform this, and in stead of speaking to the Commendation of the old Officers, I purpose to speak by way of Exhortation to the new: the Names of them are as followeth—</p>
               <p>Now you <hi>Gentlemen</hi> that are elected by the 24 <hi>Electors</hi> to these Offices, although you are to enter upon your Offices in the night, yet they are no obscure Offices, but Offices of Trust and Credit: your Predecessors these late years have had (as it were) a continuall <hi>night</hi> of troubles; yet the stars of the greater and lesser magnitude, I mean the Lords and Commons in Parliament, did afford them some light of comfort; and now I hope the <hi>day of deliverance</hi> doth <hi>dawn</hi> upon us. In that night Light was sown for the righteous, yea light did arise to them out of that darknesse, and I hope that we shall ere long see <hi>Jerusalem</hi> in good condition, <hi>and peace upon Israel.</hi> And now give me leave to take occasion from the season of the <hi>night,</hi> to give you a word of Advice, which is to keep a good <hi>watch;</hi> a good <hi>watch</hi> over your selves, and a good <hi>watch</hi> over others; you are to watch over your selves, yea against your selves, for you will finde <hi>self</hi> a very great hinderance to you in the good performance of your <hi>duties.</hi> And
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:52385:16"/> therefore beware first of <hi>self-love,</hi> that you be not carried away with <hi>by-respects,</hi> for your <hi>aims</hi> ought to be as publick as your <hi>places,</hi> and you are to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider, that you enter upon an <hi>Office,</hi> not a <hi>Benefice,</hi> and therefore should endeavour to perform your service with <hi>credit,</hi> rather then for <hi>profit;</hi> and as you heard from the Minister to day, there may be a peny sometimes as <hi>ill saved,</hi> as there may be a peny <hi>ill got.</hi> And you are also to beware of <hi>self-will,</hi> knowing that good Laws and Customs are to be your Rule for your carriage, and not your will: <hi>Sic volo sic jubeo</hi> is a very ill Motto for a Magistrate, when he shall give no other <hi>reason</hi> of his actions but his <hi>will:</hi> And therefore as <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> said to <hi>Melancthon</hi> in another case, I say to you, <hi>Luctare contra teipsum maximum hostem,</hi> strive against thy self the greatest enemy to thy self. You are also to keep a <hi>watch</hi> over your <hi>passions,</hi> especially of <hi>fear</hi> and <hi>anger;</hi> I do mean that base fear and pusillanimity of heart, contrary to the noblenesse of minde that should be in a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate, for the fear of God ought to be cherished in you; but you are not to fear the face of man in doing what is right, but to go on with Christian courage. <hi>Jacob</hi> in blessing of his sonnes, said of <hi>Judah, Judah is a young Lion,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 49. 9. 10.</note>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> And afterwards it is said <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>The Scepter shall not depart from Judah;</hi> so that men in Authority should be <hi>viri strenui,</hi> otherwise their Authority will be neglected, and the edge of their resolution taken off from executing of Justice. It was the Symbole of <hi>Ferdinandus</hi> Emperour of <hi>Rome, Fiat Justitia aut pereat mundus;</hi> and I say, <hi>Fiat Justitia ne pereat Civitas,</hi> Let Justice be done least the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:52385:17"/> City perish. I do not say that every thing should be stretched up to <hi>summum jus,</hi> and punished in severity: There may in some cases be used an <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a moderation and mitigation in such cases as are left to discretion. As for the passion of anger, that is the <hi>drunkenness</hi> of the soul, and disposesseth a man of his reasonable soul, as it were, and hinders a man in knowing and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning truth. Therefore a <hi>watch</hi> is to be kept upon that passion. Holy anger (which is called zeal against evil) is commendable, but to give way to our own passions, and by colour of the Execution of Justice, to execute <hi>spleen</hi> and <hi>malice</hi> is abominable; therefore we should use anger <hi>Ut milite, non ut imperatore,</hi> as <hi>Seneca</hi> said, As a Souldier, not as a Commander. Also you are to <hi>watch</hi> over your generall conversation, knowing that as you are set above others, so you are more conspicuous and obvious to others, and they will keep a <hi>watch</hi> upon your actions: And it is said, <hi>Magistratus virum indicat,</hi> men in Authority do discover themselves what they are. And as you are to watch over your selves, so you are to <hi>watch</hi> over others and for others; you are to take heed of friends, least they prove enemies. Justice is said to be blinde, not as if it were blinded by reason of ignorance, or of gifts, but because it may not <hi>respect</hi> persons, though it doth <hi>discern</hi> the cause. And you are to <hi>watch</hi> for the good of others souls and bodies; for their souls in maintenance of <hi>Preachers,</hi> and suppressing those houses that are Nurseries of vice; and endeavouring that the people keep a good <hi>decorum</hi> in observation of the <hi>Sabbath</hi> and <hi>Fasting daies,</hi> so as to yield outward conformity at least; that so it may be said of you
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:52385:17"/> in your kinde and degree, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>They watch for our souls.</hi> And also for the bodies of others; for the security and health of their persons, to keep the <hi>City</hi> safe and clean, and to look to the Provisions, to keep a <hi>watch</hi> over the Market, and to endeavour to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form abuses therein, and to look to the <hi>assises of Bread</hi> for the good of the poor. You are also to look to your Priviledges, Rights and Liberties, to maintain and preserve them. I must confesse that sithence these sad distractions and troubles, whilest our peace hath been interrupted, our li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties have in some respects been suspended and intrenched upon by such as fled hither for refuge: but I hope the time will come wherein it may be said <hi>Cedant arma togae,</hi> and then it will be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise. It is granted in the Charter of <hi>H.</hi> 6. to this place, That if any native should live a year and a day here, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> without claim of the Lord, he was to be free from his Lord; but I would not have such as are forrainers thereupon to conclude, by some abode here, that they have a title to the <hi>free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> of this City, and freely to work at any Trade here; but to take notice that they are to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for themselves elsewhere. To conclude, if you <hi>Gentlemen</hi> shall be pleased to keep this <hi>watch,</hi> and improve your parts and opportunities for the common good, then the <hi>Burgesses</hi> according to the said Charter of King <hi>John,</hi> shall live and hold their priviledges, <hi>benè, &amp; in pace, liberè, quietè &amp; honorificè;</hi> and you will answer our expectation, and perform your severall oathes, which now you are to take.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="speech">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:52385:18"/>
               <head>V. <hi>Jaspero Clutterbooke Arm' Majore.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>GEntlemen and friends</hi> who attend these solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Octob.</hi> 4<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. 1647.</note> Although I need not tell you what the occasion of this meeting is; yet I shall with your good leave take an occasion from the same to speak somewhat unto you of such anniversary Elections, and then acquaint you with the names of the persons elected and chosen to bear Office amongst you for this year next following, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to our Charter; which being done, I desire with the favour of the new elected Officers to addresse my self unto them in a few words of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and so to conclude. In all which I purpose to be short and yet plain. And first being to speak upon the Theam of anniversary or yearly Elections, I hold it not improper to propose some particulars to your considerations of Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions in generall.</p>
               <p>1. That there are Powers and Authorities ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercised in Civil societies, that are not by Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; some <hi>Jure naturali</hi> by the Law of nature, as the power of parents over their children, and some <hi>Jure gentium,</hi> as the powers of the Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors over the conquered: Here grew <hi>Potestas Dominorum in servos,</hi> the power of Lords over their slaves or villains, which was much known in the times of our Ancestors, and our Law-books have many cases concerning them; whence I collect that the beginning and cause of villenage or servitude to be this, That there was a great measure of community of things till <hi>Noah</hi>'s flood, but afterwards, by the multiplication of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:52385:18"/> people, came in a stricter property, and holding of things more in severalty. Then people not being contented with their own, there arose <hi>bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>els,</hi> and thereupon a constitution of Nations was made, that those that were taken in battell should be saved alive, but yet be bondmen for ever to those that took them, to do with them and theirs as they pleased. And therefore some Etymolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gists hold they were called <hi>Servi, potius à Servan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do quàm serviendo.</hi> Now in regard of the tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and cruelty of Parents and Lords in the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cising of these powers and Authorities, there have been positive Laws and Constitutions made in severall States for bounds and limitations of them.</p>
               <p>2. That in Powers and Authorities that are <hi>Jure civili vel Positivo,</hi> there Elections have place. Of the antiquity and necessity of Government you heard from the Minister in a learned Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course <note place="margin">M. <hi>Nelme.</hi>
                  </note> this morning; now I shall adde, That originally persons came to govern by Election, for although at first when there were but a few families in the world, then the Patriarchs and Heads of families governed without Election; yet afterwards when the world began to be peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled, then families grew into Societies, and made one great family as it were; and thereupon by the common agreement of the people One was set up, <hi>Penes quem imperium foret,</hi> that should have do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion over the rest for the better keeping of peace and order amongst themselves, and the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation of them from violence of strangers, who was to act in such manner as was agreed upon. And I make no doubt but the <hi>Monarchies</hi> that now are hereditary, and go by succession,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:52385:19"/> were at first either by Conquest or Election, or both, the people assenting after, which was in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of an Election: And the peoples chusing of one to bear rule, and investing him with power and authority, must needs have an influence upon all the <hi>subordinate</hi> and derivative powers and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities which he is necessitated to make and use as helps in government, as <hi>Moses</hi> who is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led King in <hi>Jeshurun,</hi> or among the righteous, by the advice of <hi>Jethro</hi> his father in law, did: And the Minister gave a good reason for it, Because where one is to govern a great people the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then is too heavy for one mans shoulders, where of some in this Kingdom are by the Common law, or the general customs of the Realm, some by particular <hi>customs</hi> of places, some by <hi>Statute law,</hi> some by <hi>Commissions,</hi> and some by <hi>Charter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Elections</hi> are manifold and various, both in respect of the <hi>Electors</hi> and the <hi>manner</hi> of Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; as sometimes Elections by Wards, by Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishes or Hundreds; answerable to which there were amongst the <hi>Romans</hi> their Assemblies cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Connitia tributa, curiata</hi> and <hi>Centuriata;</hi> also <note place="margin">Rom. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiq.</note> sometimes by <hi>Counties:</hi> And in respect of the manner, sometimes by <hi>Votes,</hi> sometimes by <hi>holding up of hands,</hi> sometimes by <hi>Lots;</hi> and that several <note place="margin">M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                     <hi>Rous in his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheolog. Attic.</hi>
                  </note> waies, as by <hi>white Beans,</hi> as of old among the <hi>Athenians</hi> in chusing of their Senators; and sometimes by <hi>guilded Balls,</hi> as now is used a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the <hi>Venetians</hi> in Election of young men to the participation of the City rights and liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: But where the Elections are by Charter, such as our Election is, as well the Electors as the manner and formalities of the Election are prescribed also. In some places according to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:52385:19"/> their Charters the <hi>Maiors, Bailiffs</hi> or other Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of <hi>Corporations</hi> are chosen by the Commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty or <hi>Burgesses,</hi> and in others by a certain number of them: And so it is with us, for our Charter having appointed the <hi>Common councell</hi> to be the <hi>Representative body</hi> of the <hi>Burgesses,</hi> hath also appointed <hi>Twenty four</hi> of the <hi>Common councell</hi> only to be the Electors. And let none of the Common <hi>Burgesses</hi> repine thereat; for in most places where the Elections have been left to all the Burgesses by the Charter, yet by experience it hath been found, that in those places, the usuall Elections have been and are by a <hi>selected number,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>See the Case of Corporati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> Co. 4. <hi>Rep.</hi> 78.</note> and such Elections have been held good in Law, and to be warranted by their Charter upon a presumption that there was at first (by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon consent of the people) some ordinance and constitution made amongst them for it, to avoid popular confusion. And as our Charter appoints the Electors to be of the Common councell, so that the elected shall be of them too, as being deemed the best sort of Citizens, as the <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stratus Patricii</hi> in <hi>Rome</hi> were chosen out of the better sort of <hi>Romans.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>4. Elections are to bear Offices either Judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all or Ministeriall or both in different respects; of which nature all ours are, that are now to be undertaken upon this Election, excepting only Master <hi>Maior.</hi> And yet (in a sense also) he may be said Ministeriall, and that not only in regard he is subordinate to higher Powers (as the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture speaks of Kings and such as are set in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority under them) but also in respect of the people over whom and for whom he is to govern, in which regard the Apostle cals the Magistrate,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:52385:20"/>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>The Minister of God for good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>These things concerning Elections in generall being premised, now I come to speak something of what I promised concerning elections <hi>annuall</hi> or <hi>renewed,</hi> year by year: touching which you must know, that our <hi>Common Councell</hi> is not cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen yearly as the Senators of <hi>Athens</hi> of old were, or those of <hi>London</hi> lately. And now I speak of <hi>London,</hi> how can I name it without an honourable thought or Christian sympathie? when I consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their labour of love towards us, and their sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular piece of service in the relieving of this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, by raising the siege that was against it? and how can you do lesse, then with me to render a thankfull acknowledgement, and afford them hearty well-wishes of peace and prosperity? I could expatiate my self in the praises of that <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther City,</hi> but I should make too great a digression, and therefore I return to the point of <hi>Annuall Elections:</hi> Our Common-Councell-men are to continue for life, unles removed for some just cause; but the <hi>Officers</hi> now chosen, are but to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in their places for one whole year, and who knows whether they shall so long: for you know that one of the Sheriffs this year M. <hi>Henry Ellis</hi> by name, had his Writ of discharge and died in his Shrievalty: but being sensible thereof, and not contented with his expressions of his love to this <hi>City</hi> before, and out of his zeal to advance mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandizing therein after his decease, he made some provisions for the same in his Will, out of his adventure at sea, thereby leaving a good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to others, and a memoriall to posterity of his publike spirit and good affection to this place.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:52385:20"/> Now for the ground thereof, I conceive this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall election was instituted out of politicall prudence, both in favour to the <hi>Officers</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, that the burthen of care, expence and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble incident to the execution of those Offices, might not lie so long upon them as to oppresse them, or endamage their estates; and in respect to the people that are to live under this govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; that those that bear Office having so short a time, may be the more active for their good, and lesse inclineable to break the rules of <hi>Justice</hi> and <hi>Equity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now although there is an yeerly election of Officers amongst us, yet it is not at their election to govern or execute their Offices by an <hi>arbitrary</hi> power, for there are known rules of proceeding and acting, partly by <hi>traditionall customs,</hi> which are <hi>unwritten Laws,</hi> as sometimes the <hi>Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> were governed; and partly by Laws, which are <hi>a written custom</hi> as the <hi>Athenians;</hi> yet there is not amongst us as it was amongst the <hi>Athenians,</hi> an <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, an yearly consideration and <hi>change</hi> of Laws, wherein the people had a great suffrage; for although <hi>(pro re natâ)</hi> as oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion requires, our Ordinances of Common-Councell and by-Laws of the <hi>Leet</hi> may be alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and others made <hi>pro bono regimine &amp; guberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione</hi> (they are the words of the Charter) the good government of the <hi>City;</hi> yet in matters <hi>Judiciall,</hi> where we are to follow the example of the supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior Courts (be they Criminall or Civill) there is one rule and set form of proceeding and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and therefore all such Causes as those Criminall and publike Causes in <hi>Rome,</hi> may be called <hi>quaestiones perpetuae.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:52385:21"/>
               <p> By this time I think you desire to know who are the Officers for the year next ensuing; and according to promise I will acquaint you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with: the Names of them are these—</p>
               <p>Now <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> you that are chosen to these Offices, give me leave to tell you, that the wishes and hopes of the <hi>Electors</hi> and of those present and absent, are and will be, That your carriage during the continuance in your Offices may commend their choice. And if please you to have patience to hear a word of advice from me to further the same, it shall be dispatcht, in presenting to you one <hi>single</hi> (and yet in my judgement singular) rule for your observance, that is, In all things to use a mediocrity, and keep the golden mean, which is a thing as beautifull in the eye of a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralist, as a symmetry and due proportion of mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers in a naturall body; whereunto <hi>Keckerman</hi> compares it. I would not be mistaken as if I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended hereby to commend unto you a detestable <hi>neutrality,</hi> or a <hi>lukewarm Laodicean</hi> temper of spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, after all your <hi>Covenants</hi> and <hi>Engagements</hi> to and with God and man, instead of a spirit of zeal, and a conscionable and vigorous perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of your duties; I mean no such thing: but my meaning is, that you should <hi>inter utrum{que} tenere,</hi> keep your selves from running upon ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremes, to steer the <hi>vessell</hi> in the midst of the <hi>channell,</hi> that it dash not against <hi>Scilla,</hi> nor be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulfed in <hi>Charybdis;</hi> wishing you may have knowledge and prudence therein to be your <hi>guides,</hi> and the glory of God and the publike good your <hi>ends.</hi> And that I may more explain my self by descending to some particulars:</p>
               <p>1. In <hi>Religion,</hi> that you keep a mean; not that
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:52385:21"/> I would have you regardlesse thereof, to be like <hi>Gallio</hi> in the <hi>Acts,</hi> to care for none of those things, whether people came to the Congregation or no, or unresolved men in the points of the object and manner of your Worship, as the <hi>Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites</hi> in the time of <hi>Eliah,</hi> who were said to halt betwixt two opinions; but yet to keep a medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ocrity in your opinions and practices, considering that what <hi>Aristotle</hi> said of Vertue, that it was <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitus in mediocritate positus,</hi> that may be also said of Truth. Truth and Vertue are betwixt errors and vices on both hands, and therefore in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture we read of deviations and turnings aside to the right hand and the left, yet although they are in the middle, they are distanced from the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremes by a <hi>Geometricall proportion,</hi> having more cognation and affinity with the one then the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as the instance may be given in <hi>liberality,</hi> whereunto <hi>prodigality</hi> comes neerer then <hi>covetous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse.</hi> Therefore in respect of your selves, you are to keep the <hi>midway</hi> betwixt <hi>irreligion</hi> and <hi>supersti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> not to be prophane, or as <hi>Horace</hi> saith, <hi>parci deorum cultores,</hi> sparing and niggardly worshippers of the deity, nor yet such as the Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Athenians</hi> in the <hi>Acts,</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 17. 22</note> we read it too superstitious, but <hi>Beza</hi> translates it <hi>quasi religiosiores</hi> too religious: You are not to place your religion in what you ought not; to make more sins then God hath made, nor lesse, but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> to go with a right foot according <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 14.</note> to the truth of the Gospel.</p>
               <p>And in respect of others; that as you are not to patronize or countenance error or heresie in any, yet on the other side you are not to be of the temper of spirit towards all dissenters, as those
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:52385:22"/> Disciples were of, who would have <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, fire come down from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven upon the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> but to use a moderation as lovers of <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>peace.</hi> And (if I may be so bold as to explain my self) I would say, that as you are earnestly to contend for, and constantly to hold fast unto the <hi>truths of Christ,</hi> so you are diligently to seek after, and carefully to conserve <hi>the peace of Christians.</hi> Perhaps, in the time where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and place where you shall bear Office, you may meet with some dissenting brethren of the same religion, then if you shall finde the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to be in points that are disputable, and as yet determinable, or that the truths concerned are of the lesser magnitude and inferior nature, so that the errors you shall discover be not in the fundamentals or touch not upon the vitals of our religion, and they are not maintained with that pertinacy, as the consequence thereof may be any notable disorder or disturbance of the civill peace; then if I may declare my opinion (and I think it differs not from that of learned M. <hi>Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,)</hi> you are to be as studious of unity as zealous of uniformity.</p>
               <p>2. In matters of Justice the Minister told you well of your duty in execution of Justice, and the blessings you and the people might expect there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by. Now I shall say that you may so do, you are to keep the mean, that in the administration of Justice both in the matters of the Crown, and civill causes betwixt party and party, there may be indifferency and equality, that in the punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of offenders there may not in the balance of Justice be <hi>underweight</hi> made through fear or favour, nor yet <hi>overweight</hi> made through igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:52385:22"/> or malice; that a mean be kept betwixt foolish pity and severity: the Wise man (that Kingly Preacher) said, <hi>ne esto justus nimium;</hi> for as <hi>peccata non sunt equalia,</hi> so there are many cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances that tend to the extenuation or ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravation of offences, which not being consider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, you will fall under that rule, <hi>summum jus sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma injuria;</hi> for, streyning all cases up to the extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of Law, may in some cases be little lesse then injury; an Emblem of this moderation you have in the Romane <hi>fasces</hi> and <hi>securis,</hi> an axe wrapped in <hi>burchen rodds,</hi> which was carried by the <hi>Lictors</hi> (in nature of our Serjeants) first be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and afterwards before the <hi>Consuls:</hi> and M. <hi>Godwyn</hi> in his Romane <hi>Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> gives this reason, to intimate the different punishment that belonged to the notorious, and petty malefactors; and another reason he gives too, that the anger of the Magistrate might be somewhat abated, whilest the rods were <hi>unbinding.</hi> And for an example you have <hi>Solon</hi> the just, the famous Lawgiver of the <hi>Athenians,</hi> who took away and abolisht <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the cruell Laws of one <hi>Draco,</hi> who punished all offences great and small alike.</p>
               <p>And as touching the deciding of Civil Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troversies, that the scales of Justice may not turn with the touch of by-respects, but onely with the just merits of the cause. Now that you may have so just a ballance and rightly make use of it,</p>
               <p n="1">1. You are to look upon the Laws with a ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious eye; for as you heard this morning, to follow your own will and not the will of the Law is not justice; you are therefore to look upon the Law, not only the letter, for <hi>Qui haeret
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:52385:23"/> in litera haeret in cortice,</hi> but on the sense of the Laws, and the ground of the making of them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To look directly on the cause, and not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely on the person, not to have a <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a respect of persons in judgement.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Not to look on things and actions <hi>in ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stracto,</hi> nakedly and barely, but in <hi>concreto,</hi> clothed with accidents and circumstances.</p>
               <p>3. As touching the collecting, receiving in and laying out of the profits and revenues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to this <hi>Corporation,</hi> that there be a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration used, not to be too slack or remisle in <hi>Receipts,</hi> or too profuse in <hi>disbursements</hi> to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of the <hi>Chamber,</hi> nor yet too quick or sharp upon the <hi>Tenants</hi> in gathering in, or too nig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardly or sparing in laying out to the <hi>dishonour</hi> of the <hi>City.</hi> And there is a thing called <hi>Hospitality,</hi> if there were any need I should say thus much, that (respect being had to the credit of your places) it is not be mean, and yet a mean is to be kept therein, not only in respect of your estates, but also the present condition of the times, as you were seasonably admonished lately by a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Divine in publique.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That in your generall carriage and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versation a mean be kept, that you be not of a haughty or harsh spirit, for though you are lifted up above others in <hi>place,</hi> yet you are not to be in <hi>minde:</hi> A Magistrate is to have <hi>spiritum magnum,</hi> a great spirit, but not <hi>spiritum elatum,</hi> a proud spirit, but to be meek, humble and affable, which will adorn Magistrates as well as others, and such vertues are not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, but well may consist with Christian courage, yet I would not have you neglect the respect due to your places out of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:52385:23"/> pusillanimity in vindication of your selves, or an affectation of popularity how to preserve your respect, you were well taught by the Minister. And you are to know, that demeanure is best in a Governour, when it is so tempered as it at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts both love and fear from the inferiours.</p>
               <p>These things I have proposed unto you in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, desiring you to make application in your severall places, <hi>reddendo singula singulis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now I think it time to wind up all, and it shall be in the expression of the Poet,</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Sit modus in rebus; medio tutissimus ibis.</l>
               </q>
               <p>I speak it to each of you, to keep the mean is the safest way, and not only so, but also comfortable and profitable for others, if you shall so de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mean your selves with a wise moderation. As therefore amongst the Ancients (in some places before the knowledge of writing and printing) it was a custome to sing the Laws that they might not be forgotten, so the people may have cause to sing that you have not forgotten the Laws and laudable examples of your prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors, and the <hi>good customs</hi> of this <hi>City:</hi> to the observance whereof each of you is to be obliged by a solemn oath, which is ready to be now ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministred unto you.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="speech">
               <head>VI. <hi>Johanne Madocke Arm' Majore.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>HOnoured Friends, Burgesses and others,</hi> Your <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Octob.</hi> 2<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. 1648<seg rend="sup">o</seg>.</note> presence here I take to be an argument ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of your good affection then of your earnest
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:52385:24"/> expectation of some new thing; for these so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnities are not so much to be accounted new as renewed, seeing our <hi>Charters</hi> and our <hi>Customs</hi> are the <hi>directory</hi> of our proceedings. I shall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore give you some account according to the usuall manner of what votes passed in the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction Chamber, touching Officers for this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent year next following, whereof some are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons newly chosen into old Offices, and others with a little remove continued in their Offices by a new election; yet thereby neither are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to action without a consecration to their Offices by oathes, which remaineth to be done in this assembly. But before the administration of the oathes, or the nomination of the persons that shall take them, give me leave to present unto you my serious thoughts of that subject, by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting you what I take an Oath to be, and the kindes thereof, with the severall forms and ends of the taking of oaths, which I shall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to do briefly and succinctly as the time ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monisheth me; and then to reflect the same by a word of application, according to the present oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion, hoping and desiring that what I shall say, may be both seasonable and acceptable.</p>
               <p>An Oath is a calling of God, or something <note place="margin">Quid fit.</note> instead of God, to witnesse for the confirmation of the truth of what is spoken. I define it thus, that I may comprehend all kindes of Oathes, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull and lawfull.</p>
               <p>An Oath may be said unlawfull either in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of the object, that is, that by which a man swears, by false gods, or by the creatures, as by the light, or any thing we eat and drink, or any other thing besides God, which is to make an idoll of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:52385:24"/> them, and the oath no better then an idolatrous oath; for the grounds of the originall institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and practise of Oaths (as I take it) were the secrecy of mans heart and Gods omniscience: It is his sole prerogative to be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the knower and searcher of the heart and conscience and of what lies hid there: Thoughts (which are said to be free in respect of the censure of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Laws, because unknown) he taketh notice of, so that we cannot without impiety give this glory to a creature.</p>
               <p>2. In respect of the subject matter, when it is against the rule of Justice, as the Oath <hi>Corban,</hi> condemned by our blessed Saviour, whereby (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to a Pharisaicall tradition) children held themselves exempt from yeelding due ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to their parents: The Anathema or oath of <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 23. 21.</note> execration which <hi>Pauls</hi> enemies took, that they would not eat nor drink till they had killed him, such oaths are better broken then kept, because the observing of them increaseth the sin of man, and consequently the wrath of God.</p>
               <p>3. Or in respect of the occasion, when it is sleight or unnecessary, it is an unlawfull oath, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the party doth swear by the true God, for it makes his reverend Name vile and contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible, by divesting it of the dignity due unto it; and is a taking of it in vain, and a plain propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of his holy Name; and therefore in the Statute against swearing it is called prophane swearing; for I conceive the motive of an oath as well as the matter, should be <hi>res gravis</hi> weighty &amp; of moment: it should be taken, <hi>necessitatis causa non libidinis aut voluptatis,</hi> as M. <hi>Calvin</hi> speaks, not for or at pleasure, but upon some necessity im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:52385:25"/> which some take to be implied in the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> which is in the passive voice, and signifieth rather to be sworn then to swear, as <hi>Juratus est</hi> among some Latin Authors.</p>
               <p>Setting these unlawfull Oathes aside as dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stable abuses of divine Majesty, I come to speak of lawfull Oathes, which is more direct to my purpose; for some Oaths I hold lawfull, contrary to their opinion, who because vain Oathes are condemned, therefore by a misconstruction will allow of none at all.</p>
               <p>As for lawfull Oathes, they are either <hi>private</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Quotuplex</note> or <hi>publike, spontaneous</hi> or <hi>constrained:</hi> But that which we call a legall Oath, or an Oath in a Law sense, is when it is administred by or taken in the presence of one or more thereunto lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly authorized.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Either for deciding of a controversie, as <hi>assertory Oaths</hi> taken by Witnesses.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Or for the performance of a trust or ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, as <hi>promissory Oathes</hi> taken by Officers or Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Or for the discovery of the opinions and affections of people, as the <hi>probatorie Oaths</hi> of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy, appointed by the Statute 1<seg rend="sup">o</seg>
                  <hi>Eliz.</hi> and of Allegiance appointed by a Statute 3<seg rend="sup">o</seg>
                  <hi>Jacob</hi> for the better discovery of Popish recusants.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Or for to oblige and engage persons to or retain them in loyalty, faithfulnesse and trusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse towards others, as the <hi>submissary Oathes</hi> of ligeance taken by subjects to the King, which hath been used in <hi>Leets</hi> or <hi>Lawdaies,</hi> and the Oath of <hi>fealty</hi> by <hi>tenants</hi> to their <hi>Lords.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As touching the forms of taking of Oaths in <note place="margin">Forms.</note> respect of gestures and words, I find them very
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:52385:25"/> different. As putting the hand under the thigh' as the Patriarch <hi>Abraham</hi> made his servant <hi>Elie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zer</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 24. 2.</note> to do, that he should not take a wife for his son from amongst the <hi>Canaanites.</hi> And as the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 47. 29.</note>
                  <hi>Jacob</hi> caused his son <hi>Joseph</hi> to do, that he should not be buried in <hi>Egypt;</hi> which I take to be rather a token of subjection, then to have any mysticall signification of Circumcision or the promised seed, because I finde it only used from inferiours to superiours; and it seems the sons of <hi>David,</hi> and chief of <hi>Israel</hi> used the same gesture in swearing fidelity to King <hi>Solomon,</hi> when he sate on the Throne, for in the original it is that they gave <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Their hand under</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Chro.</hi> 29. 24.</note>
                  <hi>Solomon,</hi> rendred by our English Translators, <hi>Submitted themselves to Solomon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. There was another gesture of standing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Altar in the Tabernacle, and afterwards in the Temple.</p>
               <p>3. There was also a gesture used of <hi>lifting up the hand,</hi> as <hi>Abraham</hi> said to the King of <hi>Sodom,</hi> that <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 14. 22</note> he had lifted up his hand to the Lord, the most high God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that he would not take any thing of his, which gesture was used in the taking of our Solemn League and Covenant; that Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, whose matter, at the time of the first taking of it, was not more cause of joy to the well-affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, then the manner of observance since, may be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cause of grief to us.</p>
               <p>But the most ordinary way with us is putting of the hand upon the Book, and afterwards the kissing of it, which is (as I conceive) as much as <hi>Amen</hi> or <hi>So be it.</hi> Which I take to be the reason wherefore it is called a <hi>Corporall Oath,</hi> in respect of the <hi>bodily ceremonies</hi> used in the taking of it.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:52385:26"/>
               <p> As for the words of Invocation or Petition, which is used in Swearing (and in respect espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially it is termed a part of Divine worship) the forms are different: omitting those used in other Countries, I will speak of those used here both in the times of the Popish and Protestant Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Heretofore when Popery prevailed here, the usual forms were, <hi>As God you help,</hi> or <hi>So help you God and all Saints,</hi> or <hi>So God me help,</hi> or <hi>So God help me and his Saints;</hi> according to the Latines, <hi>Its me Diiament,</hi> in the Comoedian, or <hi>So help me God and his holy Judgement,</hi> as in the oath of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juration: or <hi>So help them God and all Saints, and by the holy Evangelist,</hi> as in the oath of aliens Artificers. Yet in the old oath of <hi>Ligeance,</hi> the form is, <hi>So help you Almighty God.</hi> But since the Reformation the usual form hath been, <hi>So help you God,</hi> or <hi>So help me God;</hi> somewhat like to the Jewish form, <hi>Ita Deus mihi faciat:</hi> Or as in the oath of Supremacy, <hi>So help me God, and by the Contents of this Book:</hi> or as sometimes, <hi>So help me God and the Contents of this Book:</hi> By which word <hi>[Contents</hi>] I am of opinion is to be meant Christ the summe and center of the holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures; and therefore it is said, to swear upon the holy Evangelists, because they wrote the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story of Christ. The end of taking of Oathes, <note place="margin">End.</note> as the Apostle saith, is, that it should be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>An end of contradiction,</hi> gainsaying or controversie; by silencing doubts and disputes, and working a confidence, acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>escence, and a firm settlement in such for whose satisfaction they are taken. And the reason why they serve for such confirmation and assurance, is this, Because in every oath there is an Imprecati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:52385:26"/> Execration or conditional curse, which is a part of the form, and essential to an Oath: and is sometimes expressed, as in the <hi>Leviticall</hi> Law in the case of Jelousie prescribed to be taken by the wife, which was therefore called the <hi>Oath of Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing.</hi> And as the <hi>Roman</hi> Heralds, upon a Truce or a League, holding a stone in their hands, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Peream ut hic lapis è manibus decidet;</hi> which swearing was called <hi>Jurare per Jovem lapidem:</hi> or else implied or understood; as when we say, <hi>So help me God,</hi> is as if it should be said, <hi>Let me be hurt if it be otherwise.</hi> For in an Oath God is not only called as a <hi>witness,</hi> or an asset or of truth, but as a <hi>Judge</hi> and avenger of falshood; now it is not to be presumed that any one that hath any sense of Divine justice, will be so desperately wicked as wilfully to draw upon himself the smart of Divine vengeance, which is imprecated in an Oath. These things being premised I draw these conclusions thereupon.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That in this Land there is a great and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral contempt and contumely cast upon the most high God, Maker and possessor of heaven and earth, and upon his Holy and Reverend Name, by rash and common swearing, swearing by the creatures and forswearing; the serious conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration whereof might bring some damp upon our joy, seeing it ministers matter of humiliation and lamentation, and indeed better were it for us to mourn for that and such like provocations of Divine wrath in a way of humiliation, then for the Land it self to mourn in desolation, as the Prophet speaks.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That an Oath is to be taken with all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence and fear, and to be observed with all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:52385:27"/> and care; for the sincerity of intention is to be seconded and discovered by the reality o<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> actions and endeavours.</p>
               <p>I shall hold you no longer in expectation wh<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the persons are that are chosen to be Officer<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and now to be sworn, but name them to you, the four and twenty Electors have made choice of—</p>
               <p>And now Gentlemen, you that are to b<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> sworn, give leave to propose to your considerati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons a few things more concerning the taking and keeping of your Oathes. I need not tell you tha<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> an Oath is to be taken in that sense as he to whom a man swears doth understand; or that i<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is as well an evil, and in the opinion of some, I think not far from the truth; That it is a great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er evil, <hi>Jurare per Deum verum fallacitèr quam pe<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Deum fallum veracitèr:</hi> because that I have n<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cause to suspect any of you to be levened with th<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Jesuiticall doctrine of equivocation or mental reservation; but let me intreat you to consider that yov are not only to take <hi>Juramentum</hi> a com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon Oath, but <hi>Jusjurandum</hi> a solemn Oath, ye<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a <hi>Sacramentum civile,</hi> an Oath whereby ye are as i<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> were hallowed and dedicated to the service of th<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Commonwealth and this Corporation. An<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> therefore my request unto you is, that you wil<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> manifest <hi>publique spirits</hi> in your <hi>publique place<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and not to suffer the common good to be over born by private favour or fear; nor yet negle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cted for private interests. And secondly that yo<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> would remember what came from a Learne<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tongue this morning, as helps unto you in th<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Ken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick.</hi>
                  </note> execution of your Offices, that is to say, that yo<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be couragious and faithfull, countenancers <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:52385:27"/> good people, and promoters of good things, and to make repetition thereof in your practises.</p>
               <p>I must professe unto you that I have been of opinion, that it were a thing to be wished that such generall Oathes for such as are to be in of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices or services were not so common and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent as they are, for 1. It is held that the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>See</hi> Co. 11. <hi>Rep.</hi> 98. <hi>in James Bagges Case.</hi>
                  </note> breach thereof is not punishable in a Judiciall Court, and the wilfull refusall or carelesse neglect may be punished as well without Oaths as with them. 2. That man that maketh conscience of an Oath, I think will make conscience of his duty without it, being led thereunto more <hi>Virtutis amore</hi> then <hi>Formidine paenae.</hi> And lastly, there is oftentimes much difficulty in the exact perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of all particulars included within the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall words of some Oaths; so that many times the persons that take them are more ensnared thereby, then the persons for whose sake they are taken are secured. But seeing <hi>Sic volet usus,</hi> the custom of the Realm, and this Corporation pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vails to have it so, I shall not discourage you therein, but will give you a word of encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is this, that you shall finde in your oaths, in some part of them, <hi>According to your wit and power,</hi> which I do conceive is to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood as having a reference to all the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of your Oaths; so that if there shall be in you <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Graecian</hi> terms, I hope your practise will translate them into <hi>English,</hi> and in the mean time give me leave to do it, If there be in you a cheerfull, ready and willing minde, joyned with a speciall care and honest indeavour to know, and to perform your duties in your severall places, you will have comfort in
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:52385:28"/> your consciences, when you shall leave your pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and may expect that God will blesse you, and good people blesse you (as you heard this morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) and we may expect that you will be a bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing to this <hi>City.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="speech">
               <head>VII. <hi>Henrico Cugley Arm' Majore.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>HOnoured Citizens, and others here present,</hi> I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Octob.</hi> 1<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. 1649<seg rend="sup">o</seg>.</note> you expect to hear something from me, because <hi>custom</hi> doth challenge it, and therefore I purpose to say something unto you: Yet I know not whether I shall answer all your expectations, for though I desire not to displease any, yet by reason of the difference in <hi>heads</hi> and <hi>hearts,</hi> I mean, understandings and affections, in these distinguishing and dividing times; I cannot assure my self to please all; I shall therefore crave both your patience, and your fair constru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
               <p>We are come to the end of our <hi>City year,</hi> which is by <hi>Charter,</hi> I cannot say to the end of our <hi>grievances,</hi> I would I could say so, but the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this time will not afford it, neither have we any <hi>Charter</hi> whereby we may claim the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of such an exemption.</p>
               <p>The change of the year I beleeve troubles none, but the reflecting upon the changes in the year, I finde perplexeth the thoughts of many, and that not only of the vulgar, who gaze only upon the outside of things, and of whose passions their senses instead of their reason, have the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:52385:28"/> power; but also of men in reputation for wisdom, who being as doubtfull of the impul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive causes, as they are fearfull of the events of the late <hi>grand Transactions</hi> and present <hi>admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strations of Government,</hi> and applying ordinary <hi>rules</hi> to extraordinary <hi>cases,</hi> are either unsatisfied in what hath been done by others, and unresol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in themselves what to do, or otherwise very peremptory in their sentence. I must confesse the <hi>quarrels</hi> and bickerings betwixt <hi>Prerogative</hi> and <hi>Liberty</hi> have been very great in our forefathers daies, and ended for the most part in an <hi>accomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation;</hi> and in particular the great difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the King and his Nobles, in King <hi>H.</hi> 3. time, touching those things, was fairly closed up in <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> the great Charter of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> Liberties confirmed by so many Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments afterwards. The like was desired by most in the late great difference in this Nation, but many say and do beleeve it, that the <hi>Salus Populi</hi> the peoples safety would not suffer it; howsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all must acknowledge that <hi>Divine providence</hi> so ordered it, that as the disputes were unparal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leled, so the deciding of the controversie should rather make then follow a president. There have been much amazement and distemper in the spirits of the people thereupon, whereat I marvell not, because they are the proper effects of such great and sudden mutations. But to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate the one and allay the other, let us consult with our <hi>English Chronicles,</hi> they will tell us, not only of <hi>changes</hi> of Governours, but also of chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in the government of this Nation, and those accompanied with no small distractions and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stresses of the people. There we may reade of a
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:52385:29"/>
                  <hi>British Pentarchy,</hi> a Government by Five; a <hi>Saxon Heptarchy,</hi> a Government by Seven, as well as an <hi>English Monarchy,</hi> a Government by One. There we may reade how Dominion in this Nation did run in severall Lines amongst the <hi>Britains,</hi> the <hi>Romans,</hi> the <hi>Saxons,</hi> the <hi>Danes,</hi> and the <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> &amp;c. and how they had their <hi>periods</hi> at seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral times in former ages; and whether the <hi>period of Monarchy</hi> it self be now come, time will evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. In the mean time, I do conceive that submission to the will of God, and subjection to the present power of man in lawfull things, do not deserve so foul a character as some do give it. I hope I shall not be accounted to <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porize,</hi> because I declare my opinion, especially seeing I have such reason to ground the same up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that is able as I think to bear the weight of such an assertion. For if any credit be to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to our <hi>English Histories,</hi> it is apparent that <hi>power</hi> and power alone, without <hi>legall title</hi> hath been many times the <hi>supporter</hi> of the <hi>Royall arms;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">9 E. 4. <hi>f.</hi> 1. Co. 3. <hi>part. of Instit. cap.</hi> 1. <hi>of Treason.</hi>
                  </note> yet in those times I find in our Law-books That <hi>obedience</hi> to the powers <hi>De facto,</hi> was approved of, and <hi>disobedience</hi> was in those times accounted a <hi>crime</hi> not a <hi>vertue.</hi> And if I am not mistaken, the Histories of those times do afford these con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusions, 1. That the love of the people was the Princes best guard: and 2. That the submission to the prevailing powers hath been the peoples best security. Thus much (and I hope not too much) I thought good to speak unto you touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>State-affairs,</hi> the new face whereof doth affright so many. And now I come to speak of our <hi>City affairs,</hi> and am to acquaint you with the change of your <hi>Officers;</hi> but as for the <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:52385:29"/> it is so far from being changed, that it is confirmed by Ordinance of Parliament for the union of the Churches of this City, with all our Franchises and Liberties, procured by the vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant care and diligent endeavours of one of your <note place="margin">M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                     <hi>Pur<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </note> Aldermen who doth serve for you in Parliament. But before I come to name unto you the new Officers elected for this next year, I have one humble suit to make unto you all, which being for your own good I hope will be granted; and that is, that you will be more acquainted with, and give a more free entertainment to <hi>Unity.</hi> I am in earnest, and therefore shall double my request, That you will be pleased to give a more free en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment unto <hi>Unity.</hi> I desire to discourse something of that subject, that you may the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter know my meaning.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Unity</hi> is a <hi>simple Theme,</hi> and so perhaps may I be accounted for proposing it, because I doubt many look upon it as a <hi>forreigner;</hi> but if I may have liberty of speech (which I crave) I hope I shall evidence to all, and perhaps perswade such, that it doth well deserve to have the <hi>freedom</hi> of this City: I must confesse, and I am sorry there is occasion so to do: That <hi>Unity</hi> is too great a <hi>stranger</hi> amongst us, I have considered what the reason thereof might be, and I do conceive it to be the pride, self-conceitednesse and envy that is amongst us, which causeth passions, and through the mists of those passions things are looked up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and so misapprehended; thence ariseth jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lousies, evil surmises, strong prejudices, strange misconstructions of intentions and actions, and hard, and uncharitable censures thereupon, and all to the hindrance of <hi>Unity.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:52385:30"/>
               <p> We are all here in one place, but I may well doubt we are not all of one minde, that we are not here <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> with one accord, for in our time that saying is verified, <hi>Quot homines tot sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiae, Quot sensus tot dissensus:</hi> how many men so many mindes; yet it is likely there would be more <hi>unity</hi> if we would meet oftner in one place; I mean not under this roof, nor only in private Christian meetings, but chiefly in such places as commonly (though somwhat improperly) are called Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es. There was a <hi>Union</hi> made of our Churches in the year 1648. which was a worthy work and <note place="margin">
                     <hi>By Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance dated</hi> April 3. 1648.</note> tending to <hi>Unity;</hi> but this present yeer there was a Lecture set up in one of them, and that tends further, yea, more to <hi>Unity</hi> of persons then the former: for although the <hi>Ordinances of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> may unite such Churches, yet it is the <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of Christ</hi> that must chiefly unite hearts, but not unlesse his spirit joyn with them. There is in such <hi>sacred Assemblies</hi> held forth one <hi>Common salvation</hi> and one high-way unto it, mistake me not I do not say a <hi>broad way</hi> but a <hi>High way.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is likewise held forth one <hi>Common rule</hi> to walk by. Too blame are they that either out of prophanenesse of heart contemn, or out of care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lessenesse or a false opinion of perfection neglect such <hi>Assemblies,</hi> for there two words are much spoken of, and they are <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>love,</hi> both tend to <hi>union,</hi> the one of our hearts to God, and the other to one another, for <hi>Ʋnio voluntatum est dile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionis fructus,</hi> Unity ariseth from love. It would also much conduce to <hi>Unity,</hi> for all to act in their own <hi>sphere</hi> and places, for they that shall do o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise in a <hi>Corporation,</hi> if they may not be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to a divided member, that is no waies use<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:52385:30"/> to the body; yet surely they are as disjoynted limbs, whose motions are both painfull and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comely, <hi>subordination</hi> is a thing that tends to <hi>unity,</hi> subordination of inferiour <hi>persons</hi> to superiour persons, of inferiour <hi>powers</hi> to superiour powers. As subordination in the <hi>faculties</hi> of men, so the subordination of men in societies makes the <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">By <hi>M.</hi> Nelme.</note> You heard this morning very well of the benefits of <hi>Magistracy</hi> and the great inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of <hi>Anarchy</hi> or the <hi>Levelling way;</hi> which should it prevail I fear we should have cause to use the expression of <hi>Tacitus</hi> writing of the loose-living <hi>Armenians</hi> in the 2 of his Annals, that they lived, <hi>Magis sine Domino quam in libertate,</hi> rather with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Lord then in liberty; And that we should see more divisions rather then encrease of Unity. We are a <hi>City,</hi> and so as Citizens should agree; We are a <hi>Garison,</hi> and so as citizens and souldiers we should agree with one another: for which purpose I shall propose to you some means for the same, which are A friendly association each with other, a fair interpretation of each other, and a discreet condescention each to other, <hi>Cedere de proprio,</hi> To part with somewhat of propriety for <hi>unity,</hi> to bear with and to forbear each other in love, which <hi>moderation</hi> tends much to <hi>unity,</hi> for in my small observation as a middle temper of spirit betwixt a calm and a tempestuous spirit, is most serviceable to discover truth, so it is also most usefull to attain peace; and <hi>peace</hi> you know is the bond of <hi>unity.</hi> If what I have said be not sufficient to perswade unto <hi>unity,</hi> give me leave to cite you an authority, and that is of the <hi>Kingly Prophet David</hi> who saith, <hi>Ecce quam bonum &amp; quam jucundum,</hi> behold how good and pleasant a thing
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:52385:31"/> it is, for brethren to dwell together in <hi>unity,</hi> It is a <hi>pleasant</hi> thing, yea, it is a <hi>glorious</hi> thing to be in <hi>unity.</hi> What a glory it is for a City to be not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly compacted in <hi>houses,</hi> but for Citizens to be conjoyned in <hi>hearts?</hi> We are also a garrison, we have two swords, they are <hi>diversi</hi> but they should not be <hi>adversi,</hi> what a glory will it be for such a garrison that the civill and military swords are carried so uprightly and discreetly, that they clash not one against another; Yet so to conjoyn as to be ready to fall upon the head of <hi>Impiety</hi> and <hi>Iniquity</hi> wheresoever they finde it: What a praise-worthy thing will it be for that to be spoken of you as you are a City, which <hi>Salust</hi> in his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teline War writeth of the old Romans, <hi>Cives cum civibus de virtute certabant,</hi> There was no other contention amongst those Citizens but in the Aemulation of vertue: What a praise-worthy thing will it be for that to be spoken of you as you are a garrison, that there is no contention betwixt Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens and souldiers, but who should go beyond each other in the offices of love: yea it is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly matter of praise, but will be a means of profit for people to live in Unity. You will finde the old Proverb verified, <hi>Concordia res crescunt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It will advance your trading in time of peace, and in time of trouble it will be a support of your spirits, yea, tend to the safety of your persons and estates. <hi>Vis unita fortior,</hi> you that were here in the siege of this City can write a <hi>Probatum est</hi> upon this, that Unity tends to Security, when a nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and potent enemy came before you, came against you, and round about you, yet were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced to depart from you, because God was with you; and as a means of your safety stirred up
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:52385:31"/> your hearts to stand one with another upon your guard. By that action you got encrease of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, the honour of <hi>fidelity</hi> was added to your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Antiquity;</hi> but I must tell you, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by you contracted also proportionable hatred and envy from the adverse party, and so much that I beleeve not a few persons in <hi>Gloucester,</hi> but <hi>Glou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cester</hi> it self is the object of their malice. Then it will be safer for you to conjoyn for your preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, then to comply with that party, for if a reconciled enemy hath been held so dangerous, what shall we think of an enemy <hi>enraged,</hi> and upon professed terms of revenge. I hope there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that fatall simplicity will not fall upon this City to rely upon our enemies, more then our friends. We should then unite as Citizens, as Citizens engaged, as Citizens delivered, as Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens devoted to ruine by the adverse party, in case they should prevail. You may perhaps be willing to demand of me what unity I mean: To that I say, that Unity which hath <hi>Verum &amp; Bonum</hi> joyned with it, such a unity as is accompanied with truth and honesty, Whereas I have spoken to you concerning the <hi>goodnesse of unity,</hi> I hope you do conceive I mean no other <hi>unity</hi> but an <hi>uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> in goodnesse, otherwise it may be rather called a <hi>conspiracy</hi> then an <hi>unity:</hi> some of you perhaps may object that it is a very difficult thing for us to agree, there are such differences in these times in <hi>Spiritualibus &amp; Temporalihus,</hi> touching matters of Religion and the Common-wealth; yet may not we <hi>convenire in aliquo tertio?</hi> Have you not seen many lines run into one Center? Have you not seen sometimes diverse waies all leading to one place? May not many sounds in musick being
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:52385:32"/> well modelled make a good consort? Are not there in naturall bodies <hi>Elements,</hi> not only of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent but of contrary qualities, yet being well tempered do agree <hi>in uno composito?</hi> I must con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse that there are too many differences in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and practise in these times, yet where they tend not to destroy <hi>fundamentals</hi> in <hi>religion</hi> or to crosse the main ends of the <hi>Covenant,</hi> why may not we agree as Christians, as Englishmen, as Covenanters for all that? and why not we joyn together in our endeavours to preserve and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the Protestant Religion, and the English Liberty which were the main grounds of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement of the honest party?</p>
               <p>Some of you also perhaps may object, that we have many burthens, burthens breed discontents, and discontents divisions; I must confesse we have many burthens, I wish they were fewer: But let me expostulate a little with such, Will justling each with other ease us? or will it be wisedom for us to go those waies as may endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger the breaking our <hi>necks</hi> to save our <hi>shoulders?</hi> Complaints are frequent in our mouths, but I wish there were lesse cause of them, and that we had more patience. We should not joyn in mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murings for our burthens, much lesse in repining at mercies, or envying the instruments from whose hands we receive them.</p>
               <p>Have we no mercies to put into the other scales of the balance? what are our religion, our laws, our liberty, our property, our health, fruitfull seasons, and victories obtained by our friends (which puts us in hope of the reducing of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and setling of <hi>England)</hi> are not these mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies? should not we therefore rather joyn in
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:52385:32"/> praises to the God of our mercies, and joyn in praier to him to continue them. And that he would give wisedom and right aims to all our Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nators and Counsellors of State, valour and si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity to our Seamen and Souldiers, and good successe to all their endeavours relating to our welfare? Having spoken thus much to you of unity, I come to give you the names of such as are elected to joyn as props in this government the year next folowing, which are as followeth.—</p>
               <p>And now M. <hi>Maior</hi> and the rest that are <hi>newly elected,</hi> I shall make my humble addresse unto you in a word of advice, partly by way of <hi>Appen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dix,</hi> and partly by way of <hi>Rehearsall</hi> of some of the seasonable and wise advice, you had given <note place="margin">By <hi>M.</hi> Nelme.</note> you this morning in another Assembly. You are to execute severall offices, yet are to be as severall archers standing in severall places, yet aiming at one mark, and that as the <hi>Common welfare</hi> of this City. In order whereunto, you are not only to have your thoughts of keeping up the port and state of your City, maintaining of your privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges and liberties, or improving of your reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues, which things are very commendable. But also to be patrons of Religion, by using your best endeavours that the Sabbaths may be duly obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, the Ordinances of Christ frequented, and faithfull Ministers encouraged. Also it is expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted that you take care that provisions may be made for the poor, provisions of work for the idle, and of relief for the needy. And this further motion I shall humbly make for these <hi>Paupers,</hi> that the late additions to their yearly mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance so fresh in memory, may not blunt but sharpen the edge of your endeavours, to make
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:52385:33"/> further provisions for them: Also that you look to the disorders of Alehouses, whose number should rather be lessened then encreased. And that you look to the Assizes of bread and beer this dear time. You are also to be a refuge to the oppressed, a terrour to evil doers, and a security to all good people, in good causes, by what names or titles soever distinguished. And lastly to be a good example to all: what hath been done by your predecessors herein, I commend to you to be imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated, and what ought to have been done, I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly propose it to you to be supplied. Now before you are to execute your offices, you are to take an Oath, a new Oath, such an Oath as hath never been taken in this place, prescribed by the State for the uniformity of the Nation; and if you shall joyn in the taking thereof, you will give some testimony of your <hi>unity.</hi> I shall not paraphrase upon the Oath, but leave the matter thereof to your construction, as the Act whereby it is enjoyned leaves the form of the taking there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to your election.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="speech">
               <head>VIII. <hi>Jacobo Stephens Arm' Majore.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>HOnoured friends,</hi> Your solemn presence and <note place="margin">
                     <hi>An.</hi> 1650</note> attendance here, seems to demand of me an account of the votes upon the debates above in the <hi>Election Chamber,</hi> which I am provided to give you; but before I tell you the persons, whom <hi>providence</hi> hath designed to bear Offices in this <hi>City</hi> this next year, I crave your favour
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:52385:33"/> that I may take <hi>Providence</hi> for my <hi>Theme,</hi> and speak a little of that, of which in these our times so much is spoken.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Providence</hi> I take to be nothing else but the <note place="margin">Quid fit.</note> outgoings, and exercise of that infinite wisdome and almighty power, in and about the conserva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, government and disposition of all creatures &amp; their actions, which at first manifested it self in the creation of the world. Or more briefly thus: The execution <hi>in time,</hi> of what was decreed <hi>before time;</hi> so called from the infallible foreknowledge and immutable counsell of God. Now in advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing this <hi>Providence</hi> I must dethrone the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens blind goddesse <hi>Fortune,</hi> yet shall not allow of or establish the <hi>Stoicall Destiny;</hi> neverthelesse I must acknowledge, that in respect of man and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond causes, some <hi>events</hi> may be said casuall or contingent, which in respect of God (who as the Philosopher saith, is <hi>Ens Entium &amp; Causa Causa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,)</hi> are all necessary and brought to passe by the counsell of his own will: And also that God in the waies of his providence, doth ordinarily out of his indulgence rather then necessity, use the concurrence of second causes; although he doth not so tye himself to them, as to act onely within the <hi>sphere</hi> of their <hi>activity,</hi> but sometimes acts <hi>above</hi> them, and sometimes <hi>without</hi> them, when he is pleased to work those works which the Greek call <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and the Hebrews <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>great wonders,</hi> to the amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and astonishment of the sons of men.</p>
               <p>This providence extendeth to all things and actions, g<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eat and small, good and bad. Good actions (as Divines speak) are by <hi>divine operation,</hi> and bad by <hi>divine permission,</hi> and both are as well
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:52385:34"/> governed by the wisdome and power, as they are wrought <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> by his determinate counsell. God hath an <hi>eye</hi> and <hi>hand</hi> in the <hi>wheels</hi> of all things; yet the chief good is not nor can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be the author of any evill, although he can bring good out of it; for though in the evill actions of men, the <hi>naturall motion</hi> is from the holy God, yet the <hi>morall transgression</hi> is from sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full man; who though in his sinfull acting, to the fulfilling of his own will, he doth (though not intentionally) fulfill the <hi>secret</hi> will of God; yet he is not thereby excused of his offence against the will of God <hi>revealed</hi> in the holy Scriptures, the rule of mans life; but is thereby made liable to <hi>Justice</hi> as a transgressor of a <hi>divine Law.</hi> By this <hi>providence</hi> all that <hi>checkerwork</hi> is wrought in all humane affairs, wherein the divine power is said (as it were) to sport it self, <hi>Ludit in humanis divina potentia rebus.</hi> Hence it is that poor mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals have so many sunshine and cloudy, good and bad daies, and so much <hi>April weather,</hi> I mean variety of prosperous and adverse passages of <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence,</hi> which do so change the condition of poor creatures in this <hi>sublunary</hi> world, in matters relating to their souls, bodies, estates and names, that like the influence of the <hi>Moon</hi> upon the <hi>wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> doth cause the ebbing and flowing of their <hi>comforts</hi> in this present life. By this <hi>providence</hi> Nations have had their encreasing, flourishing and decaying in power and glory: Hence it hath been, that some Nations have had so large a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion so long as their <hi>day</hi> lasted; that they have shone in glory upon the earth like the <hi>Sun</hi> in the firmament, darkning the <hi>glory</hi> of all their neighbours, till their <hi>Sun</hi> did set, and the black
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:52385:34"/> curtains of the <hi>night</hi> overspread them. I will give you an instance hereof in the three famous <hi>Monarchies</hi> of the world, the <hi>Assyrian, Persian</hi> and <hi>Graecian,</hi> that <hi>tript</hi> up one anothers heels, and <hi>trampled</hi> one upon another, and became succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sively the <hi>mistresses</hi> of the world, but have all lost their <hi>commands.</hi> And as for the <hi>Romane Empire</hi> that now is, it is not as it was; for the <hi>Imperiall Cedar</hi> hath been sensible of so long and continued an <hi>Autumne,</hi> that it hath lost not only some of his <hi>leaves</hi> but <hi>branches</hi> also.</p>
               <p>By this <hi>providence</hi> have been the constitutions, alterations and translations of <hi>Government:</hi> for though man be the subject and instrument in all changes, yet the ultimate resolution must be into Gods will, as the prime and supreme cause of the beginnings, continuance and periods of govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the nations of the world; wherein it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth the God of heaven and earth many times (to use the words of the <hi>Magnificat)</hi> to throw down <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 1. 52.</note> the mighty from their <hi>seats,</hi> and to exalt them of <hi>low degree.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By this <hi>providence</hi> Nations are either upon termes of <hi>amity</hi> or <hi>hostility</hi> one with another; up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on termes of <hi>unity</hi> or <hi>division, conjunction</hi> or <hi>opposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> within themselves; hence it is that they have the <hi>Halcionian daies</hi> of peace, or the <hi>stormy daies</hi> of war, yea sometimes of intestine wars, called <hi>Civil,</hi> although they are most <hi>uncivil</hi> and dreadful wars,—<hi>Nullos habitura Triumphos,</hi> as <hi>Lucan</hi> speaketh, wherein the <hi>victories</hi> do scarce afford <hi>Triumphs,</hi> such warres have been lattely in the <hi>bowels</hi> of our Nation, like a <hi>mighty wind,</hi> that hath so shaken the <hi>foundations</hi> of Government, that the <hi>English Monarchy</hi> its self is fallen down
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:52385:35"/> and broken into pieces; and it hath raised so great a <hi>dust,</hi> that some of our <hi>Starres</hi> have quite lost their <hi>light,</hi> and others are overshadowed with <hi>clouds of dishonour,</hi> that did sometime shine bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this our <hi>firmament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By this <hi>providence</hi> it was, that during the late warres, and the later contests abroad, so many <hi>sonnes of Mercury</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> (pardon my expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion) I mean so many wise <hi>polititians</hi> and great <hi>souldiers</hi> of the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Parliamentary party, have so often not found their <hi>heads</hi> nor <hi>hands,</hi> and they and their party have been so often constrained to find their <hi>heeles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By this <hi>providence</hi> it was that so many of their <hi>secret plots</hi> have been discovered, and so many grand and hopefull <hi>designes</hi> have miscarried, that either they have not come to the birth, or been blasted from heaven upon the first putting in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution; so that <hi>iniquity</hi> hath been often forced to cover her face and stop her mouth, whilest the wrath and fury of man hath opened our lips in <hi>praises of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By this <hi>providence</hi> it was that this City during the late warres, became so eminent for self pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation and promoting the publique interest; and (as I take it) we are yet indebted to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for that mercy; and I conceive it will be no lesse vertue for us to <hi>keep</hi> our honour, then it was to <hi>get</hi> it.</p>
               <p>By this <hi>providence</hi> this last year our <hi>Counsels</hi> at home have been so prosperous, and the <hi>actions</hi> of our Armies abroad so victoriously successefull, even to envy and wonder: That thereby we have some further hopes of the lengthening of our tranquility, and security of our enjoyments, and at
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:52385:35"/> the length in some processe of time, of the lesse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of our burthens.</p>
               <p>To conclude, By this <hi>providence</hi> it is <hi>that</hi> we are, and <hi>what</hi> we are; and that the affairs of this and our neighbour States are as they are. But if any shall demand of me Why it is thus, I must confesse it a hard question, but yet shall give this answer thereunto. Though the book of ordinary <hi>providences</hi> is like the volume of <hi>nature,</hi> written in so large and common a <hi>Character,</hi> and with such plainnesse of <hi>phrase</hi> that the things contained in them are obvious to <hi>vulgar</hi> capacities; yet the book of <hi>providences</hi> extraordinary, is both for the <hi>letter</hi> and the <hi>stile</hi> so strange and obscure, that it doth oftentimes puzzle the sharpest eyes and most refined understandings, that they can hardly pick out the meaning of them; yea some of the leaves thereof, which contain <hi>Arcana im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perii</hi> the unsearchable secrets in the government of <hi>providence,</hi> are wholly closed up, and not to be opened till the day of the <hi>revelation</hi> of all things; so that no man can finde out the work that God makes perfectly, or to use the <hi>phrase</hi> of the <hi>Royall Preacher,</hi> From the beginning to the end, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> And as for some works of <hi>providence, Nec intellectu nostro penetrare, nec pro arbitrio nostro immutare possimus,</hi> we can no more understand then alter them: Yet notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this great difficulty to demonstrate all <hi>provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences</hi> by all the <hi>causes</hi> thereof. I may say of the works of <hi>providence</hi> as the <hi>Kingly Prophet</hi> said of the works of <hi>nature, There is no speech nor lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage where their voice is not heard,</hi> and in some measure understood. It is regularly true that in the school of <hi>providence,</hi> Successes do not in and
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:52385:36"/> of themselves, without the Word of God, teach us positively and necessarily, the goodnesse or badnesse of persons or things, so as certainly to conclude love or hatred from them; yet in so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn <hi>appeals</hi> to heaven in doubtfull cases, not determinable by the Word, <hi>events</hi> have been heretofore held to speak in the language of a <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine sentence</hi> for humane satisfaction. And it is an agreed case, That <hi>Gods rod and staff,</hi> comforts and crosses, have their <hi>voices,</hi> and do reade us generall <hi>lectures</hi> of the <hi>creatures vanity, Gods All-sufficiency;</hi> and something also that tends to <hi>faith in God</hi> and <hi>repentance from dead works,</hi> and happy are they that can learn such lessons from <hi>provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</hi> Furthermore, as to all the passages of <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary providence</hi> they do bespeak our <hi>acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement</hi> of God, as being wrought by his hand; but the passages of <hi>Extraordinary provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> being wrought by his strong hand, and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stretched arm, do bespeak our <hi>admiration.</hi> And as to all passages of <hi>providence,</hi> the Divine Word doth command silence to all carnall reasonings about the reasons and ends of Gods proceedings, and doth give a <hi>check</hi> to all impatient expostu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 20.</note>
                  <hi>Who art thou that disputest against God?</hi> Whereas man should quiet his spirit before him, under all his dispensations; for although perhaps the carrying on of his <hi>designs</hi> in the world may crosse some of our <hi>interests,</hi> we ought to put our <hi>hand</hi> upon our <hi>mouthes</hi> because he hath done it. And although the works of Gods <hi>providence</hi> may up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their first appearance seem to us like to some of the first <hi>productions</hi> of <hi>art</hi> and <hi>nature,</hi> rude, grosse and ill favoured; yet <hi>Solomon</hi> that <hi>oracle
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:52385:36"/> of wisdom,</hi> said of every thing God makes, It is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> fair or beautifull in colour and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion in his time or season. A memorable example of calmnesse of spirit that <hi>King of Spain</hi> gave when he heard of the disastrous miscarriage of his <hi>great</hi> otherwise called <hi>Invincible Armado, That he sent his Ships to sight against</hi> England, <hi>but not against the Deity of heaven.</hi> And if you will have <hi>Scripture</hi> examples, take good old <hi>Ely,</hi> when the <hi>rod</hi> of God was shaken over him; and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient <hi>Job</hi> when he was under the <hi>lash; It is the Lord,</hi> saith the one; and <hi>Blessed be his Name,</hi> saith the other.</p>
               <p>And now having spoken thus much of provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in generall, I come to speak of a particular passage of <hi>providence</hi> in the <hi>election</hi> of our <hi>new Officers,</hi> for whom I have reserved a few words, least having spoken of <hi>providence</hi> I my self should be accounted very <hi>improvident</hi> in spending all the <hi>stock</hi> of my allotted time in generals. Now what <hi>Solomon</hi> saith of <hi>Lots</hi> I may say of <hi>Votes,</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>The whole judgement or disposition is from the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The names of the Officers elected are—</p>
               <p>And now <hi>Gentlemen elected</hi> to these several Offices in our <hi>City Government,</hi> I shall more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, although more briefly, apply my self to you. I shall humbly propose unto you <hi>providence</hi> as worthy of your most serious consideration. And I shall desire you to stand in <hi>Janus</hi> posture, with a face towards the <hi>old year,</hi> and another to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the <hi>new,</hi> that you may the better <hi>observe</hi> and <hi>serve</hi> the Government of <hi>providence.</hi> If you take a view of the passages of <hi>providence</hi> in this year
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:52385:37"/> last past, you will finde, that there have been u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sual performances of <hi>religious exercises</hi> without restraint and disturbances; some further en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements to <hi>vertue,</hi> and discountenancing of <hi>vice,</hi> by the putting in execution of some <hi>good new Laws</hi> made by the <hi>Supream power</hi> residing in <hi>Parliament,</hi> that there have been some further <hi>provisions</hi> made for the encrease of the <hi>Revenues</hi> of the <hi>Chamber,</hi> and the maintenance of the poor in the <hi>Hospitals</hi> by the purchase of <hi>Fee-farm Rents,</hi> and some better accommodation for the keeping of the <hi>Tolsey Court</hi> by a stately structure. <note place="margin">The new Talsey.</note> That there hath been a <hi>friendly compliance</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Citizens and souldiers, I wish the same may continue: That for the generall, things have been in a very <hi>peaceable</hi> condition, and the bodies of the inhabitants, for the most part in a <hi>healthy</hi> constitution; And that the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and reputation of your City hath been up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held and maintained. And the means that have been serviceable to <hi>providence</hi> herein, have been the pious and just disposition, the vigilant and faithfull care, the industrious and active indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, and the generous and prudent deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of those worthy instruments, that having been intrusted for you, have accordingly endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to promote the common welfare of this City. All which being duely weighed, as they may challenge from the Citizens in generall <hi>gratulation,</hi> so they will afford unto you in spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall, that are to succeed in Office, matter of <hi>instruction.</hi> And now for the year that is to come, wherein you are to act your severall parts: It is beyond my reach to prophesie of future e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents; neither do I think you should be so soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citous
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:52385:37"/> about the <hi>successe,</hi> which belongs to God, as studious and industrious to dischage the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall <hi>duties</hi> which belong to you, this is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly attended with a blessing; for it is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimentall truth, that <hi>To do well,</hi> is the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary rode way <hi>to have well:</hi> But then the <hi>pace</hi> you are to keep is <hi>festinare lentè,</hi> to act upon delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; and for your <hi>guide,</hi> that you may not misse the way, I shall commend that morall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept which <hi>Alexander Severus</hi> (though a Pagan) liked so well, as to make it his Motto, <hi>Quod tibi hoc alteri,</hi> Do as you would be done unto; and so doing, it will be your <hi>wisdom</hi> to eye God in the waies of his <hi>providence,</hi> and to take such due notice of his seeming <hi>smiles</hi> and <hi>frowns,</hi> in good and bad <hi>successes,</hi> that you may gain some ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage thereby. I shall also recommend unto you the text this morning, <hi>Honorantes, honorabo,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. 30.</note> and do desire your endeavours to put in practise those worthy instructions of the <hi>Preacher,</hi> which <note place="margin">M. Fox.</note> I shall thus <hi>epitomize;</hi> That you should im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove your power and parts for the honour of God, That so honouring him by way of <hi>reflexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> (as he was pleased to term it) he may ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour you by way of <hi>retalliation;</hi> and as you now have the honour of <hi>approbation</hi> upon the entring into your Offices, you may have the honour of <hi>commendation</hi> when you shall leave them; and also maintain the honour of your City, the <hi>Civil Government</hi> whereof is now to be committed to you, and the well managing thereof is expected from you; for assurance hereof, we should be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to take your bare words, but custome and the Charter do require your oaths, which now are to be administred unto you.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="speech">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:52385:38"/>
               <head>IX. <hi>Antonio Edwards Arm' Majore.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>HOnoured and beloved friends</hi> here assembled, Whom in respect of your several qualities <note place="margin">
                     <hi>An<seg rend="sup">o</seg>
                     </hi> 1651<seg rend="sup">o</seg>
                  </note> and degrees, I may not unfitly term the <hi>summe</hi> and <hi>abridgement</hi> of this renowned City.</p>
               <p>Your solemn posture here doth seem to invite me, to make some Prologue or Preface to what is now to be acted in this <hi>Theater.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I shall take the boldnesse so to do in a brief Discourse, and I hope not unsutable to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent occasion.</p>
               <p>Time, which is held in the Schools to be <hi>Quantitas fluens,</hi> not a permanent but a flowing quantity, may be said to have a kinde of a cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular motion, like to the courses of the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Moon</hi> that measure it. A ring is a fit emblem for the year, which by a revolution endeth where it did begin; so doth our City year, which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving had his several seasons, like so many <hi>Colons,</hi> or members in a sentence, is now in a good season come to a <hi>Period.</hi> This day is the <hi>Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pick</hi> of our year, wherein our chiefest City Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, together with the burdens incident there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, are turned over from them that have born them, unto some other persons, who are chosen in their rooms to undergo them.</p>
               <p>The <hi>soul</hi> of power and authority which did <hi>animate</hi> and <hi>actuate</hi> our chief Officers in mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging our City Government this last year, is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to depart from them, they being <hi>in extremis,</hi> and by a voluntary <hi>emission</hi> and facile <hi>transmigra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to passe into the Gentlemen newly elected,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:52385:38"/> who I hope will not only succeed them in their places, but also in their endeavours of <hi>Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> the advancement of the <hi>common welfare</hi> of this City, and maintenance of the <hi>publique peace</hi> of this Commonwealth; wherein I may truly say, and I hope without offence, that amongst others <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Maior</hi> hath this last year, been so much exemplary, that he hath deserved to be put in the <hi>Catalogue</hi> of those that are ranked in the <hi>Superlative degree.</hi> I shall acquaint you with their names, and then having delivered to you some short observations upon our late delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and afterwards made my particular appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation in a word of advice to the Officers ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, I shall conclude, Their names are—</p>
               <p>As for the Stewards or Chamberlains of our City (who much resemble the <hi>Quaestores urbani</hi> in old <hi>Rome)</hi> they are (by a kinde of necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) to continue in their places, yet not without a new election: the experience of whose former actings hath begotten in us a confidence that their future administrations will be such as shall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come good stewards in the year succeeding, which I wish they may finde more peaceable and lesse chargeable.</p>
               <p>Amongst the many memorable passages of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall providence that have been conspicuous in our <hi>Horizon</hi> this last year, the most eminent and remarkable was the strange <hi>march</hi> and stranger <hi>defeat</hi> of the <hi>Scots</hi> Army, whereof I may say, as a Learned Doctor doth of many works of nature, that it requires our <hi>wonder</hi> as well as our <hi>enquiry:</hi> and Gods pleasure therein may silence all, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though perhaps it will scarce satisfie some, This Northern Army like a black cloud in a calm and
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:52385:39"/> fair season, suddenly appeared, and rouled apace hitherwards, threatning a <hi>storm</hi> to this place, if not timely prevented; but the good hand of the Lord of Hosts (in his gracious forbearance of us notwthstanding our ill deservings) kept back that formidable Army from us, whose design reached unto us, as we are credibly informed. By means whereof that dreadfull tempest fell upon our neighbour city: which out of a belief of the <note place="margin">Worcester.</note> enemies strength, and fear to make resistance, through distrust of her own, and perhaps out of a desire in some to promote the enemies design (it were very uncharitable to think so of all) entertained if not welcomed those forreign guests, for which at last they paid so dear, and that in a severe impartiality, without distinction of persons differing in affection, or putting a difference betwixt an errour and a crime. Whose sad condition how can we but commiserate? if we consider what force and violence, what ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours and affrightments: what losse and damage they sustained and we escaped? And who can take offence if I should declare the Citizens of <hi>Worcester</hi> to be fit objects of your pity, yea, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them of your liberality? which the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens themselves (guided only by the candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light of nature) did exercise to very enemies subdued, and did account it no small part of their piety so to do. I might tell you how conquering <hi>Caesar</hi> used so much Civility in that kinde, that it was said of him <hi>Odio civiliter usus,</hi> he used his hatred civilly: but I need not go so far for an example, you have it in the present Victorious <note place="margin">The Lord Generall Cromwell.</note> Generall, whose noblenesse of spirit hath been discovered, not only in gaining of conquests but
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:52385:39"/> also in his deliverance toward the conquered, so that he hath thereby gained a good report out of the mouths of enemies themselves. Let none of us therefore be so flinty breasted as to insult over the miserable in that poor City, and to shut up from them our bowels of compassion, which the Heathen Poet accounted to be so inhumane as to exceed belief,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nec mihi credibile est quenquam insultare jacenti.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yea rather should we raise their disconsolate, and dejected spirits (especially of such as are well af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected by stretching out an <hi>officious hand</hi> in mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>string to their necessities, then to adde affliction to the afflicted. I therefore commend their case to you, and wish that they may have cause to commend your <hi>charity</hi> to them. Some of the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of this Garison (as I have heard, and to their praise be it spoken) have already in their pity and bounty to them led the <hi>Van,</hi> and I hope we shall not be unwilling to bring up the <hi>Rear.</hi> Let us consider that what befell them might have befallen us, whose preservation is to be ascribed not to merit but to mercy. Had their sad Trage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy been acted here, the change of your conditions would have changed your <hi>habits;</hi> from <hi>scarlets</hi> to <hi>blacks,</hi> and would have occasioned daies of <hi>mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> instead of feasting: and wo, and lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in stead of the voice of joy and-glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse. But hitherto the Lord hath holpen us, so that <hi>Gloucester</hi> is become another <hi>Ebenezer.</hi> It continueth <hi>A City saved by the Lord, a Maiden City,</hi> not hitherto ravished by any <hi>sons of violence,</hi> as the three sister Cities have been, whilest this <note place="margin">Worcester, Hereford, Bristoll.</note> City hath been a City of <hi>refuge,</hi> and a port of <hi>safety.</hi> Let me therefore send one winged Mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senger
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:52385:40"/> to Heaven, in this Virgin-Cities behalf (whose servant I am) O that the Lord would be pleased to say to <hi>Gloucester</hi> as sometimes he did to <hi>Israel</hi> by the mouth of his Prophet <hi>Hosea: I will betroth thee unto me in faithfulnes, and thou shalt</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hos. 2. 20.</note>
                  <hi>know the Lord:</hi> I think I should not mistake if I said, that the late <hi>danger</hi> we were in was as well a <hi>mercy</hi> to us as our <hi>deliverance,</hi> though not so great; in regard there was thereby a fair oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity given to this City, and readily embraced, to vindicate and clear her self from some fowl aspersions which the hand of jealousie, if not of envy had cast upon her, to spot and stain her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation. The apprehension of danger wrought in us some fear, and the more because we had deserved a scourge for our unthankfulnesse for former mercies, and fear quickned us up to acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in making preparations and provisions to give a repulse to the enemy, in case of an assault (knowing it would be too late to take up the buckler after the wound received) which was done with so cheerfull and unanimous industry and resolution (your chief Magistrate and other good Assistants of the Aldermen his Brethren, encouraging others by their own example) as hath I hope given a clear demonstration not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of this Cities care of self-preservation, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so of fidelity to the Parliament, as may for the future <hi>non-plus</hi> and put to silence the tongues of whispering detractors. This action was perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by Citizens and souldiers for their mutuall support and safety, yea, Citizens themselves tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned souldiers <hi>hac vice.</hi> Therefore upon this <hi>triall</hi> how can I but expect as well as wish a better un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding, and a closer union betwixt the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizen
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:52385:40"/> and souldier, even that they may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned in affection as they have been in action? But though I hold our fears in this sense to be a favour, yet I must acknowledge our <hi>deliverance</hi> from the evils feared to be a farre greater fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour.</p>
               <p>This <hi>deliverance</hi> was at a greater distance then <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gloucester siege laid Aug.</hi> 10. <hi>Thursday, raised Sept,</hi> 5. <hi>Tuesday. An.</hi> 1643.</note> that in 1643. of the raising of the siege, and by reason thereof the damage was not so great to our countrey, yet the benefit, and advantage little lesse to our selves or to the State. This delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance (as well as that) was in the harvest sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, and in the same Moneth of <hi>September,</hi> were the enemies cut down; which being so near in time, and both of so grand concernment, had not the Parliament appointed the day of this <hi>sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall victory</hi> to be yearly observed, I should have advised that this additionall mercy might by way of an Appendix have been conjoyned unto the former in our yearly commemoration, seeing the enemies of the Parliament in both received a fatall blow, and were disappointed of the <hi>harvest</hi> of their hopes. And now not only the instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of our safety have better assurance of the rewards of their faithfull service; but also the well affected throughout the whole nation, put upon a greater expectation that the <hi>Iron age</hi> will shortly cease, and golden times take place; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in may be reaped with joy the fruit of all that precious seed which for many years last past have been sown upon the <hi>publique faith</hi> with tears and drops of bloud, in a further and more certain fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ition and enjoyment of a more pure and vndefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led religion, together with a godly Magistracy and Gospel-Ministery, which two grand Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:52385:41"/> in a Christian state are for Ornament, and for establishment, like to <hi>Jachin</hi> and <hi>Boaz</hi> the two stately pillars of brasse set up in the porch of <hi>Solomons</hi> magnificent Temple, and also in the <note place="margin">1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 7. 21</note> settlement of a profound and confident peace; and in the administration of so universall and impartiall justice, that the cause shall be every where more looked upon then the person,—<hi>armisque potentius aequum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Right become more powerfull then might; to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with a more full and absolute freedome of our persons, consciences, and estates, from <hi>Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall</hi> oppressions, the best tokens undoubtedly of a true <hi>Jubilee,</hi> and the truest Characters of a flourishing Common-wealth. And why may not the promises that have been made by those that are in power, serve to bottom our hopes, that so right a use will be made of our admirable succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, as shall pave a ready way to the speedy ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complishment thereof; unlesse in judgement to this Nation, for the ingratitude and disobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence thereof some possessed with the spirit of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us</hi> in the Comedy, or of <hi>Demas</hi> or <hi>Deotrophes</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in sacred writ, I mean, some turbulent, or ambitious persons, either meditating their own revenge more then their countries peace, or minding the things of the world and their own private wealth more then of God and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, or seeking the advancement of themselves, their families, and friends, rather then of Christs Kingdom and the publique good, should by any open disturbances or close con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivances, throw in any blocks to obstruct the same. And though it is dishonourable for us to imagine that the <hi>supream powers</hi> will not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantly
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:52385:41"/> aim and shoot at the right mark, after their so many professions and publique declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions made of their good intentions seconded with some beginnings of reformation; yet let us help them by our praiers to him that is higher then they; that they may be enabled so to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove their many victories, that we may not thereby become more safely miserable, but that our expectation of the enlargement of our pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, and lessening of our burthens may in due time be fully answered: so that in future times we may comfortably reflect upon our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Autumn as being the spring time of our prosperity. Some do much doubt that this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth will come much short of the glory this Nation had whilest it was a Kingdom, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they suppose the great Luminary of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge will be eclipsed by the interposition of some that are all for changes, and to bring things to a levell, and who are so moon-blinde that they cannot see the worth of learning, but having themselves little or no acquaintance with it, are but small friends if not enemies unto it; but I am of another opinion, because our Noble Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall is <hi>Chancellor</hi> and <hi>Maecenas</hi> of one of our <note place="margin">Chancellor of Oxford.</note> chief Seminaries of Learning, and thereby is deeply engaged in the protection of the Schools; And I hope will be as famous for cherishing of <hi>Arts,</hi> as he is already for bearing of <hi>Arms.</hi> But I must not expatiate and walk further in this <hi>field,</hi> lest being so late I should forget my way home; and therefore leaving this forreign dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course I shall now confine my self to what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns our Cities jurisdiction, and make my hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble addresse to you M. <hi>Maior elect,</hi> and the rest of
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:52385:42"/> the Gentlemen that are to bear office this next year, Gentlemen, you are to take care of the City-wealth, yet not to neglect the Common-wealth, and in order to the promoting of both, you are in your places to maintain the true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and to walk in that excellent <hi>Robe</hi> which the Learned Preacher this day brought out of a <note n="*" place="margin">The holy Scriptures.</note> rich <note place="margin">
                     <hi>M.</hi> Nelme</note>
                  <hi>Wardrobe,</hi> the <hi>robe of righteousnesse</hi> perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and politicall, habituall and practicall, which he presented to you with a divine charge, that you should put it on. It was that <hi>Robe</hi> wherewith <hi>Job</hi> that was a good man and a good Magistrate was cloathed withall. And I shall present unto you also another <hi>Robe</hi> that will be an Ensign of honour to you as well as the former, and that is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the garment of humility: for humility in a high e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state is a singular ornament, and the Apostle doth command you to put it on also, <hi>Be ye cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with humility.</hi> I desire also to present unto you something more that may be usefull for your eyes and hands, and that is that you are to be <hi>observa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi> of the manners of the people, that are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the limits of your authority, that they may be kept in peace and good behaviour, and to be conservators of this City, together with the just liberties, priviledges, customs, and revenues there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. This will be for your credit and comfort, and the benefit of such as shall live under your go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, who shall (as you heard this day) thereby have occasion, to blesse God for your good performance of what you are now by Oath to undertake.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="speech">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:52385:42"/>
               <head>X. <hi>Willielmo Singleton Armig' Majore.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Honoured Citizens,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>VVE are come hither to change the <hi>Scene,</hi> and therefore I am to present other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons unto you, who are to <hi>act</hi> their parts in our City government in the year next following: for you all know that our elections are Annuall, the reason of that policy I take to be, lest by a longer continuance in Office, the <hi>Offices</hi> by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of the incident charges and troubles thereof, should be overburthensome to the Officers, or the <hi>Officers</hi> by their manner of administration be overburdensome to you. This day our City year doth end, and another year begins; like to the lines in the <hi>Athenian Tables,</hi> wherein their Laws were written <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>ordine retrogrado,</hi> as Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en plough, turning out, and presently turning in; here is no intermission, for the <hi>terme</hi> of our go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment admits of no <hi>vacation;</hi> therefore upon the <hi>exit</hi> of the old Officer, there is the <hi>intrat</hi> of the new; or rather upon the entrance of the <hi>new</hi> Officer, the <hi>old</hi> goeth out. Now give me leave as well to look <hi>backward</hi> upon the year last past, as to look <hi>forward</hi> towards the yeer that is to come, and to speak something of both; which you may please to take as my <hi>New years gift</hi> upon this our <hi>New years day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This year hath been a year of great <hi>Eclipses</hi> of
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:52385:43"/> the two great <hi>Luminaries</hi> of Heaven the Sun and Moon; but they have not been so <hi>dark,</hi> nor yet their effects or consequences so <hi>dismall</hi> hitherto to us, as to make <hi>annum tenebrosum</hi> a dark year: for neither the <hi>Parliament,</hi> nor yet the <hi>Pulpits,</hi> neither the <hi>Courts</hi> nor <hi>Corporations,</hi> have been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der such <hi>Eclipses</hi> as some feared, and others desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. I cannot say we have any assurance that they shall not be hereafter; for as all things under the <hi>Sun</hi> are subject to <hi>vanity,</hi> so all things under the <hi>Moon</hi> are liable to <hi>changes.</hi> And as for the <hi>peace</hi> of this Commonwealth, that hath been continued; and as for <hi>successes</hi> abroad they have been obtein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. When I said <hi>peace,</hi> I said much in one word, for where <hi>peace</hi> reignes like a <hi>Queen,</hi> she is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with many other blessings as her <hi>Ladies</hi> of honour; but I did not say, nor yet intend so much thereby, as the <hi>Hebrews</hi> do by their <hi>Shalom,</hi> which we interpret <hi>peace,</hi> for thereby they denote all prosperity and fidelity; And whereas I said <hi>suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesses,</hi> I would thereby hint out unto you, how the <hi>English valour</hi> by land and sea, hath been this last year crowned with <hi>victory:</hi> which although it may afford matter of <hi>thanksgiving</hi> and <hi>rejoycing</hi> yet (in the opinion of some wise men) not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out some <hi>trembling,</hi> if we consider how much we are at peace with <hi>errour</hi> and <hi>vice,</hi> and how much we are at difference with our <hi>neighbouring States</hi> For this year, the bond of Amity, so long conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued betwixt the <hi>English Oakes</hi> and the <hi>Low countrey Willowes</hi> (which were held the surest con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates in regard of their reciprocall interests) is broken asunder, which hath occasioned some <hi>storms</hi> at sea, whilest we have had a <hi>calm</hi> upon the land. From <hi>entreating of us</hi> in Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> dayes, they
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:52385:43"/> came to <hi>treating with us</hi> in after times; and now they have proceeded to a higher degree even of <hi>fighting against us.</hi> This passage of providence, causeth sadnesse to sit upon the spirits of many, who fear what the event may be: At which as I do not marvell, seeing one Emblem whereby we <note place="margin">M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Howell in his Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest.</note> were represented, was two Pitchers swimming together, with this Motto, <hi>Si concutimur frangimur,</hi> if we clash we are broken; so I wish it may not so come to passe, but rather that it may produce a closer union betwixt us and the United Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces; or if that may not be, that howsoever neither this Nation, nor yet the Protestant cause may be disadvantaged thereby.</p>
               <p>Two of the concommitants or attendants of our <hi>peace</hi> I shall mention to you; and they are <hi>plenty</hi> and <hi>health:</hi> It hath been a year of <hi>plenty</hi> for the food of <hi>man,</hi> though in many places of some scarcity for the food of <hi>beasts.</hi> I must con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse it hath been a year of <hi>drought,</hi> but (through Gods mercy to us) it hath not been a year of <hi>dearth,</hi> because the staff of <hi>bread</hi> was not broken. It hath also been a year of much <hi>health</hi> to this <hi>Countrey,</hi> but very eminently to this <hi>City;</hi> so that though our Phisitians have encreased, yet their practise hath not this last year, and I hope I shall not be blamed, that I say I am not sorry for it. I would I could speak as much of the <hi>Wealth</hi> of the City as I have of the <hi>Health</hi> of it; but I must ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge (and that with some sadnesse) that the <hi>trade</hi> of this City hath been this last year under some <hi>eclipse,</hi> and some of our Citizens have been obscured: what are the true causes thereof, I shall not take the boldnesse at this time to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine; but I will make so bold as to acquaint
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:52385:44"/> you with three severall opinions thereof, and leave you to be judges thereupon.</p>
               <p>The first is, that many of the <hi>Gentry</hi> are much cooled in their affections to this City, because it hath so constantly adhered unto, and so faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully acted for the Parliament: if this be true, there is the greater reason, that at length some re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence should be made for our great losses by <hi>fire,</hi> susteyned for the Parliaments sake.</p>
               <p>The second is, that when this City had lesse <hi>security,</hi> then it had more <hi>trading,</hi> and that if the Garrison might be removed from it, the ancient trade would return unto it.</p>
               <p>The third and <hi>last</hi> (though as I take it doth not carry with it the <hi>least</hi> reason) is this, That when this City had more <hi>zeal</hi> in Religion, then here was more <hi>quicknesse</hi> in Trade; and that if the <hi>Churches</hi> might be fuller at Gods market-times, then our <hi>shops</hi> at our market times would not be found so empty.</p>
               <p>To this decay of trade upon the <hi>Land,</hi> I might adde the losses of divers of our Citizens goods by <hi>water</hi> by a sad disaster; both which do shew us the vanity of things <hi>below,</hi> and may instruct us to set our mindes more upon those things that are <hi>above.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having made these short glosses upon the text of the last year, I come now to say something of the year next following.</p>
               <p>I shall not speak by way of <hi>prediction</hi> to tell you what will come to passe, for who knoweth what is in the <hi>womb</hi> of time? or what will be the <hi>births</hi> of this next year? our Judiciall Astrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers are bold undertakers this way, out of their pretended knowledge of the aspects, and influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:52385:44"/> of the <hi>Coelestiall bodies:</hi> but some others are of opinion, that as probable and rationall conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures may be made by observing the <hi>courses</hi> of men, and considering the <hi>state</hi> of things upon the <hi>earth;</hi> which I shall not presume to do, but leave it to those <hi>sons of wisdome,</hi> who can better discern <hi>effects</hi> in their <hi>causes</hi> then myself: yet this I shall adventure to say, being warranted thereunto by the Kingly Preacher, the <hi>Oracle of Wisdome,</hi> that there shall be no new thing but what hath been done already. For as eloquent M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  <hi>Fuller</hi> speaketh, <q>This world affordeth no new accidents, but in <note place="margin">In the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle before the Holy-Warre.</note> the same sense wherein we call it a new Moon, which is the old one in another shape, yet no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then what it hath been formerly.</q> Instead of <hi>prophesying</hi> I desire to give you a word of <hi>advice.</hi> Let the <hi>mercy</hi> of God to us this last year, be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted by us as <hi>engagements</hi> of our better serving of him, and of one and other in the Offices of <hi>love</hi> this next year. Let the <hi>Supream Authority</hi> of this Nation (under whose <hi>shadow</hi> we are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected) have your <hi>prayers</hi> as well as your <hi>purses,</hi> that they sitting at the <hi>helm</hi> of this great Ship of the Commonwelath, wherein we are all embar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, may <hi>steer</hi> their course in the managing of their affairs, so piously and prudently, that it strike not upon the <hi>sands,</hi> or dash against the <hi>rocks,</hi> and so suffer shipwrack.</p>
               <p>Let the good <hi>service</hi> done by the <hi>old Officers</hi> this last year for the Commonwealth, this City and your selves, advantage them somewhat in <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation</hi> amongst you, and let such as have done double <hi>service</hi> have double <hi>honour.</hi> And amongst them let M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Maior that hath had the chiefest place in the <hi>government,</hi> sit in the uppermost
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:52385:45"/> room of your <hi>estimation.</hi> And as for the <hi>new ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Officers,</hi> let them finde your ready compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, during the year next ensuing, in all the wayes of observance and assistance, as occasion shall require; whom that you may the better know I will acquaint you with their Names.—</p>
               <p>And now M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Maior elect, and the rest that are chosen to bear office in this City this next year let me make my humble addresse unto you; you are chosen to offices of <hi>trust,</hi> and I hope you will be <hi>trusty</hi> Officers. You had a good lesson this morning for your good behaviour, and I think you are all bound to it; I shall make a short re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition <note place="margin">By M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                     <hi>Heane.</hi>
                  </note> of it; you must be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> without ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> without complaint. I shall make this further addition, you are entrusted with the honour and profit of this City: the <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> thereof consists chiefly in the maintenance of true <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Justice,</hi> together with <hi>hospita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> to Citizens and strangers, which may be said in some sense <hi>due,</hi> although it should be done <hi>freely.</hi> The <hi>profit</hi> thereof consists in the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of your <hi>liberties</hi> and <hi>priviledges,</hi> together with the well ordering of the <hi>revenues</hi> thereunto belonging.</p>
               <p>Let me commend one thing further to you, I hope none will account it a matter of <hi>superstition,</hi> although perhaps some may a work of <hi>supereroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and that is, that you would (together with others) joyn your shoulders to hold up the stately fabrick of the Colledge-Church (the great <hi>Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of this City) which some do say is now in danger of falling. Now although for the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of your duties, we need no other assurance then your words, and could (out of our good
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:52385:45"/> opinion of you as the <hi>Athenian</hi> Judges did by <hi>Xenocrates,</hi> who gave testimony before them) cry out that you should not take your <hi>oathes;</hi> yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it is otherwise appointed, I am to invite you thereunto; and I wish you may be as care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to observe them, having taken them, as I hope you are now willing to take them. And so I have done.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Page 22. line 18. for <hi>Warwick.</hi> read <hi>Worcester.</hi> page 30. line 13. for whereof some, reade some Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="catalogue_of_names_of_officers">
            <pb facs="tcp:52385:46"/>
            <head>A CATALOGUE of the NAMES of the several Officers in the several Years afore-mentioned.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">Years.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">Maiors of the City of <hi>Glou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cester.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">Coroners of the County of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Gloucester.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">Bailiffs of the City. and Sheriffs of the County of the City of <hi>Gloucester.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">Stewards or Chamberlains of the City of <hi>Gloucester.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1642 1643</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Dennis Wise</hi> Alderman.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>John Scriven</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derman.</cell>
                     <cell>Edw. Wagstaffe, James Wood.</cell>
                     <cell>Brian Jenings, Thomas Witcomb, John Purlewent, William Russell.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1643 1644</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Nich. Webb</hi> Alderman.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Dennis Wise</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derman.</cell>
                     <cell>James Stephens, Robert Tyther.</cell>
                     <cell>John Purlewent, John Browne, John Singleton, William Bubb.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1644 1645</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Luke Nourse</hi> Alderman.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Nicholas Webb</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derman.</cell>
                     <cell>Toby Jordan, John Edwards.</cell>
                     <cell>William Russell, William Bubb. John Browne, Robert Hill.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1645 1646</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Laur. Singleton</hi> Alderman.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Luke Nourse</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derman.</cell>
                     <cell>Anthony Edwards Walter Lane.</cell>
                     <cell>Thomas Cooke, Henry Knowles, James Comelin, Jeffery Beale.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1646 1647</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Jasper Clutter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>booke</hi> Alderm.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Laurence Singleton</hi> Alderman and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards <hi>John Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>docke</hi> Alderman</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Tho. Prichards, Henry Ellis,</hi> and afterwards <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Paine.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Thomas Cooke, Henry Knowles, James Comelin, Jeffery Beale.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1647 1648</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>John Madock</hi> Alderman.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Jasper Clutterbooke</hi> Alderman.</cell>
                     <cell>Thomas Peirce, Thomas Lugg.</cell>
                     <cell>Nicholas Webb, William Scudamore, Richard Massenger, John Tomes.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1648 1649</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Henry Cugley</hi> Alderman.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Laurence Singleton</hi> Alderman.</cell>
                     <cell>William Clarke, Richard Taylor.</cell>
                     <cell>Richard Massenger, Thomas Trippet, William Scudamore, John Madocke.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1649 1650</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>James Stephens</hi> Alderman.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Henry Cugley</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derman.</cell>
                     <cell>Robert Tyther, William Fowler.</cell>
                     <cell>Thomas Trippet, John Madocke, William Russell, William Stapp.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1650 1651</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Anthony Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi> Alderm.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>James Stephens</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derman.</cell>
                     <cell>Henry Robins, Daniel Lysons.</cell>
                     <cell>Samuel Brewster, John Perks, Thomas Yate, Godfry Ellis.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1651 1652</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>William Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gleton</hi> Alderm.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Anthony Edwards</hi> Alderman, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards <hi>Tho. Hil.</hi> Alderman.</cell>
                     <cell>John Purlewent, Thomas Witcomb.</cell>
                     <cell>Sanuel Brewster, John Perks, Thomas Yate, Godfry Ellis.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>